<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Adam's condition in paradise discovered wherein is proved that Adam had right to eternall life, in innocency, and forfeited it, for him and his : also, a treatise of the lawful ministry, and the manner of Sion's redemption opened, in answer to a book of George Hammond ... / by Hezekiah Holland ...</title>
            <author>Holland, Hezekiah, fl. 1638-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44156</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2424</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20188</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12562371</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12562371</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63260</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44156)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63260)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 319:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Adam's condition in paradise discovered wherein is proved that Adam had right to eternall life, in innocency, and forfeited it, for him and his : also, a treatise of the lawful ministry, and the manner of Sion's redemption opened, in answer to a book of George Hammond ... / by Hezekiah Holland ...</title>
                  <author>Holland, Hezekiah, fl. 1638-1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 43 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for George Calvert ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Geo. Hammond's book is, in part, an answer to a letter sent him from Mr. Rutton, about a former dispute between them, about original sin, &amp;c."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hammon, George. --  Discovery of the latitude of the loss of the earthly paradise by original sin.</term>
               <term>Sin, Original --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63260:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63260:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Adams Condition IN PARADISE DISCOVERED: Wherein is proved, That <hi>Adam</hi> had right to Eternall Life, in Innocency; and forfeited it, for Him, and His.</p>
            <p>ALSO, A Treatiſe of the <hi>Lawful Miniſtry;</hi> and <hi>The manner of</hi> Sion's <hi>Redemption</hi> opened: In Anſwer to a Book of <hi>George Hammond,</hi> a Taylor, of <hi>Biddenden</hi> in <hi>Kent;</hi> who calls himſelf Paſtor of Chriſt's Church there: (And affirms, that <hi>Adam's</hi> Sin did bring but Temporal Death on him, and all in his Loyns; and that all his Enjoyments, in <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> were Earthly; That none yet are in Heaven or Hell; That the Jews ſhall return to their own Land, and enjoy it; That Chriſt ſhall reign in Earth a thouſand years, &amp;c.) The truth is aſſerted, and proved; and the Errours refuted,</p>
            <p>By <hi>Hezekiah Holland, Anglo-Hibernus</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Sutton-Valence</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Geo. Hammond's</hi> Book, is, in part, an Anſwer to a Letter ſent him from Mr. <hi>Rutton,</hi> about a former Diſpute between them, about Original Sin, &amp;c.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Who is this, who darkens counſel by words, without knowledge?</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Job 38.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Deſiring to be Teachers of the Law, but underſtanding neither what they ſay, or whereof they affirm,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Tim. 1.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>—Contentionis quàm veritatis cupidiores,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cic. Orar. l. 89.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>George Calvert,</hi> at the Half-Moon in the New Buildings in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1656.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:63260:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:63260:2"/>
            <head>To his benevolous Friend, Mr. <hi>Maximilian Taylor</hi> of <hi>Sutton.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOu remember how <hi>George Hammonds</hi> Books were ſpread in my Pariſh: was it not time for me to look to my people? I took his Book, and (by way of preaching) anſwered and confuted its errours: when, I remember, you took notes, covetous to enform your own ſpirit of the truth; What you once heard preached, you have here printed by your timely encouragement. And indeed, though I owe more then my ſelf to many friends in and about <hi>Sutton</hi> (as to your noble Couſen Mr. <hi>Edward Taylor,</hi> of <hi>Holling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born;</hi> to my ingenious Friend, M. <hi>Edw. Knatchbull</hi> of <hi>Sutton;</hi> to my bountiful Friend, Mr. <hi>Tho: Tyndall;</hi> to my Cordiall Friend, Mr. <hi>James Lamb</hi> of <hi>Sutton</hi>) yet this Book owes its ſelf to you (next to my ſelf) of all men under Heaven. For it lay by me as a dead thing, forgotten, till you revived my muſe, and your encouragements gave life to my Book. When <hi>Satibarzanes</hi> (who revolted from <hi>Alexander</hi> the great) challenged any of his Souldiers to fight, (as <hi>George Hammon</hi> almoſt doth the Clergy); <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rignis</hi> an old, but ſpirited man, accepted the Challenge, with that expreſsion: What Souldiers <hi>Alexander</hi> once had, Il'e ſhew you; and at the firſt On-ſet, ſlew him. 'Tis a folly to think to conquer an <hi>Anabaptiſt, perſuadebis &amp; non perſuaſeris,</hi> ſuch will take no anſwer. If I can
<pb facs="tcp:63260:3"/>ſtrengthen my own people, I am well enough: for, my thinks, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar <hi>Motis</hi> (in <hi>Eraſmus</hi>) ſaying, that to go about to confute <hi>Hammon</hi> is but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to meaſure the ſand, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when I conſider the many; errours in his Book, I am thinking how he might have excuſed all with that jeſt in <hi>Lipſius, ſi vera dico agnoſcite</hi> (thoſe are rare); <hi>ſi fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa ignoſcite,</hi> (that's moſt of four Book.) He much ſpeaks againſt learning, <hi>&amp; Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge</hi>-knowledg: 'tis wiſht he had more of their knowledge, that his book might have had fewer errours; but in that, he is but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. I finde errours of moment in his book not tolerable in a Common-wealth.<note place="margin">R. Anſw. in the Book.</note> As that <hi>Adams</hi> ſin brought on him, and all in his loyns but temporall death, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Hence no Children eternally loſt, or need Baptiſme: (yet the Apoſtle ſayes,) One mans offence brought condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on all, <hi>Rom. 5.</hi> were we not by nature Sons of wrath? twice dead? by nature, and otherwiſe? <hi>Jude 12.</hi> Nay, born altogether in ſins? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>John 9.</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the Phariſees obrayding the blind man. How the whole man was infected, is ſome difficulty: but as the blind man ſaid, <hi>John 9.25.</hi> this one thing I know, I was blind, and now I ſee, and we did once ſee (in Adam) and now are naturally, miſerable, poor, blind and waked, <hi>Rev. 3.</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, all in Adam ſinned onely againſt the firſt Covenant; but that the breach of that Covenant merited no more then temporall death, I deny, becauſe of <hi>Rom. 5.18.</hi> That the ſouls of Adams Progeny were in Adam, according to ſubſiſtence, I have proved, not according to eſſence. When the ſouls were created in diſpoſed bodies, is contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted,<note place="margin">Tract. <hi>4.</hi> de Anim. rat. Queſt. <hi>1. Pag. 327.</hi>
               </note> yet <hi>Euſtachius</hi> concludes <hi>in maribus circa di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em a conceptu quadrageſimum, in foeminis circa octogeſimum;</hi> only excepts our Saviours body, whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception was extraordinary. Another errour is, holding that actuall ſins onely,<note place="margin">Sum of Relig: Pag. 92.</note> make men Veſſels of diſhonour, <hi>p. 22.</hi> Dr. <hi>Uſher</hi> denies ſin to be the cauſe of Reprobation (and
<pb facs="tcp:63260:3"/>that truly) onely the means to bring it about. Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree to be glorified in mercy and juſtice, is the firſt cauſe of all. Were not ſome fore-ordained to condemnation? <hi>Jude 4.</hi> read <hi>Exod. 9.16. Prov. 16.4.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icked made for the day of deſtruction. God raiſed up <hi>Pharaoh</hi> for temporall ruine; but why not for eternall? it ſeems he hated him, nay hardened firſt his heart, <hi>Exod. 7.3.</hi> ſo perſons are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probated by the means of ſin, and thouſands for onely A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams; being by nature Children of wrath, and dying out of Chriſt. Again he denies Hell in being at preſent,<note place="margin">See Anſw. in the Book.</note> or any in glory as yet, contrary to <hi>2 Pet. 2.8.</hi> Indeed ſuch an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion was once, as appears by <hi>Revel. 14.13.</hi> but Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation cryed it down, verſ. <hi>6.</hi> The great Humaniſt Dr. <hi>Fotherbey</hi> in his learned book againſt Atheiſts (given me by a good Friend) proves that Atheiſts are much tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with fear at their dying hour.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Tho: Barber <hi>of</hi> Char<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>l. 2. c. 13.</hi> becauſe of hell. And are not all ſouls of Saints alive unto God, <hi>Luke 20.38?</hi> vvhere are ſouls departed? aſleep for ſo many thouſand of years? did not <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> talk with Jeſus? <hi>Matth. 17.</hi> I thought <hi>Peter</hi> knew not what he ſaid: it ſeems it was <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> who talked in their ſleep to Jeſus. Why did God command a reward at Even to be payd to labouring men? <hi>Mat. 24.14.</hi> ſince thoſe who labour unto the death for him, have no reward till day of judgement? I will not much longer trouble you (Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi>) but refer you to the book:<note place="margin">Ep. Ded. to Sr. Tho: Moore.</note> 
               <hi>jamque tuum non meum</hi> (in the words of <hi>Eraſmus</hi>): only when <hi>George Hammond,</hi> or any of that judgement ſay,<note place="margin">De vol. Dei.</note> that God would ſave more then he doth, believe them not, though <hi>Matth. 23.37.</hi> ſpeak that Language at firſt ſight. <hi>Lombard</hi> or <hi>Moulin</hi> will enform you, that Chriſt did gather all or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to life out of <hi>Jeruſalem (ipſis ſacerdotibus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentibus</hi>) though the Scribes and Phariſees were unwilling to have it ſo. Who can hinder Gods work? <hi>Iſay 53.13.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:63260:4"/>But to end, I fear my ſtudying to be brief, makes me too ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure. I paſſe by <hi>George Hammonds</hi> jeeres, as telling Mr. <hi>Rutton,</hi> that Hell was under his Coat: I could tell him, that except he repent of his errours, I would not be in his Coat one day, for—And 'tis well (though he call him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe Paſtor) if <hi>Cyprians</hi> words may not be made good of him and ſuch,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> Ep. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Non fidei duces ſed perſidiae magiſtri, Nam paſtores ſunt impoſtores</hi> — but farewell Sir,— You know I am making haſte for <hi>Ireland,</hi> and 'tis well if my friends ſalute me not with the Poets vvords,<note place="margin">Hom.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; having been ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from them above a dozen years. Pray God make this poor pains of mine beneficiall to his people. <hi>Sir,</hi> I am your loving Friend and Servant.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Sutton-valence</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Febr. 3. 1655.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Hez. Holland.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:63260:4"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </lg>
            <bibl>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</bibl>
            <pb facs="tcp:63260:5"/>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:63260:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To</hi> George Hammond, <hi>of</hi> Bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denden <hi>in</hi> Kent.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ne of your judgment, having preſented me with your book; which being dedicated to the Clergy, I thought with my ſelf, that if I ſhould have paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it by in ſilence, you might have ſaid I was ſuch an one as your ſelf, according to <hi>Pſal: 50 21.</hi> or unable to anſwer you: for I confeſs you have gotten into great repute with thoſe who know not how to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict you. You have the ſubſtance of all your Book anſwerd, and your material quotations of Scripture, I confeſs your Treatiſe of Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal ſinne, has more witty (if not wicked) arguments in it, than any piece written by any Heretick, ſince the Reſurrection of our Saviour to this hour: and I know I have the Epitome of all Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours or Hereſies from Chriſts time, to this, lying by me. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall be larger in anſwering that part of your book, but briefer (yet full enough) in conſidering <hi>Sions</hi> Redemption, being not ſo material. You have quoted many texts of Scripture, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the purport or meaning thereof, as ſhall appear: I wonder a man for liberty of Conſcience, ſhould force the Text of Holy Writ to take your part <hi>volens nolens</hi> againſt the intent of the Spirit thereof: But I begin to conſider your Examination of Mr. <hi>Rutton's</hi> Letter about Baptiſm and Original Sinne,</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:63260:6"/>
            <head>George Hammonds <hi>Examination of Mr.</hi> Ruttons <hi>Letter,</hi> examined.</head>
            <p>VVHere you ſay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page 9.</hi> Sprinkling of Infants is Baptiſme.</note> that ſprinkling a little water in the face of a Child, is not Baptiſm, but a cozening ſhift brought in, by Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the 3d. (what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance you have gott with Popery of late!) and that <hi>Baptizo</hi> doth not ſignifie ſprinkling (bue <hi>Rantizo</hi> doth) but onely to plunge, or over-whelm in water. Magiſterially ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken! Here I muſt conſider, firſt, that ſprinkling is nought. 2. Infant baptiſme, a cozening ſhift. 3. Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the firſt Author of it. To the firſt, <hi>baptizo</hi> is taken for dipping or ſprinkling often: as <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>He ſhall baptize you with the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> And pray, are not ſanctified men rather ſprinkled then plunged with the ſpirit? Are we not imperfect here below? know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in part, and ſanctified in part? Again, in <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.22. Chriſt ſayes, he has a Baptiſme to be baptized with, mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that of his<note n="*" place="margin">Eſt ergo bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſma triplex; fluminis, flami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, et ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</note> Paſſion; (as <hi>Paraeus</hi> on the place.) Now Chriſt was rather ſprinkled, than plunged, in regard of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man. Suppoſe the Thorns were on his head (indeed we read not of their pulling off) and Nailes and Spear wounding alſo, yet he was not wounded in each part of his body:<note place="margin">Jo. 20.25.</note> Therefore, this Baptiſme rather was ſprinkling then plunging. And remember how the Parallel lies between <hi>John's</hi> Baptiſme with water, and Chriſts with ſpirit, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.5. So if Chriſts giving the ſpirit (compared to powring, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63260:6"/>of the few drops in the Law) be rather ſprinkling (for Chriſt onely was plunged with it (receiving it without mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) ſo was his Water-baptiſme, or elſe the Parallel is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, which the Evangeliſt from Chriſt urges: But what think you of that known place, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2: All our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, To dip or ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> To plunge, vide Paſor on the word, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, theſe much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer.</note> baptized in <hi>Cloud and Sea:</hi> 'Twas Water-baptiſme, yet they went on dry ground: ſome water might ſprinkle on them from the Sea, as they walked through, and a Cloud doth fall by drops (as Experience teſtifies) more like to ſprinkling, than plunging; eſpecially conſidering how little rain falls in thoſe parts, where <hi>Iſrael</hi> then was, if we will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve Travellers; or Reaſon, becauſe of the Suns exceſſive heat drying up the Clouds.</p>
            <p>But what think you of the ſprinkling of bloud in the Law, ſo often mentioned? <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.19. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>He ſprinkled the people.</hi> Was not it a type of Chriſts bloud cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the bloud of ſprinkling, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.24. And why ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſprinkling on Infants (ſignifying Chriſts bloud ſhed for them) be counted Baptiſme, ſince the word will carry it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you believe 'tis the muchneſs of water, and not the ſprinkled bloud of Chriſt (ſignified by Baptiſme) doth the work? <hi>Peter</hi> was once for a kind of plunging, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13. till better catechized by our Saviour, <hi>ver.</hi> 9, 10. I am ſure the Promiſe was of ſprinkling, * <hi>Ezek,</hi> 36.25.<note n="†" place="margin">Sanguine Jeſu Chriſti, <hi>ſayes</hi> Trem, <hi>on the place.</hi>
               </note> and a Goſpel-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. <hi>Annotations of Aſſembly</hi> refer us to <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.26: for a farther illuſtration of the place: Chriſt gave himſelf for the Church, that he might ſanctifie it and cleanſe it by the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of water, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Sowhat ſprinkling is in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> is waſhing in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Expoſition; and why not ſometimes uſed indifferently, ſince the word <hi>Baptizo,</hi> and Texts of Scripture will hold it out. The old <hi>Common-Prayer Book</hi> allowed of Dipping or Sprinkling, if our Climate could at all times ſuffer it. Our great Fonts in <hi>England</hi> ſhew our former Cuſtome; both have been uſed, Dipping and Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: but no way will pleaſe you, if Children be baptized, which we ſhall conſider anon: onely I wonder how the Jaylor and his could be plunged (baptized they were, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.) 'twas night, <hi>ver.</hi> 33. and in likelyhood, in the Priſon, into which he ſprang with a light, <hi>ver.</hi> 29. For though it's
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63260:7"/>ſaid he called them forth, <hi>ver.</hi> 30. (that is, out of the inner priſon into which they were thruſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 24.) yet they are but brought into his houſe afterwards, <hi>ver.</hi> 34. So that the Jaylors houſhold came out of the houſe to the Apoſtles, not the Apoſtles into the Jaylors houſe to preach: but be it in Gaole or Houſe; where was water enough to plunge him, and his in ſo dry a Countrey? Did he venture, trow, to carry them to ſome River; his fear, if not his care, hindred. But had they a large tub of water there, and were they plunged: How came they, being very wet, to ſit at meat preſently with the Apoſtles rejoycing?<note place="margin">Nos pro baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>antiſmum potius habea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus hoe eſt aſperſionem. Zep. de Sacram. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lix. vide Mr. Hall quarctect, pag. 114.</note> But I forbear, perſwading my ſelf, they were contented with ſome ſprinkling: of which, ſayes one, inſtead of Baptiſme, we have rather (the word bearing both ſignifications) uſed <hi>Rantiſme,</hi> conſidering the cold climes wherein we live. Yet I ſay, not that <hi>Baptiſme</hi> and <hi>Rantiſme</hi> are quite the ſame; but that <hi>Baptizo</hi> ſignifies Sprinkling ſometimes, as well as Dipping: read <hi>Leigh Cr. Sacra in verbum,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Featley, Dipper dipt.</hi> Circumciſion to <hi>Iſrael</hi> was as Baptiſme to us: now that was not but in one part, read <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. and the Hebrew word for baptiſing <hi>(tabhat)</hi> ſignifies Waſhing in part, or Dipping: Read <hi>Joſh.</hi> 3.15. and the feet of the Prieſts that bare the Ark were dipped in the brim of the water: The word <hi>Baptizo</hi> doth ſignifie as much, therefore uſed for Sprinkling, moderate Waſhing, or Dipping; not Plunging. What the Apoſtle calls Waſhing, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.10.13. (in Greek, <hi>Baptiſmous</hi>) he expounds himſelf by Sprinkling, <hi>ver.</hi> 19.21. in Greek, <hi>Rantiſmous:</hi> ſo that <hi>Baptizo</hi> ſignifies Sprinkling; for their Baptiſmes, or Ceremonious Waſhings, were Sprinklings. We read of 3000. baptized at once, and no mention of any Rivers, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.41. Therefore, in all likelyhood, Sprinklings were there uſed. But, to draw to a concluſion, we deny not, but Baptiſme may include Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping; but ſince it includes Sprinkling alſo, we uſe that out of care and tenderneſs to Infancy: For as the Sabbath was made for man, ſo Baptiſme for our good, and not detriment; and therefore Sprinklings, in cold Climates, to be uſed ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſince the word will bear it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Infant Baptiſme proved.</note> But I come to the ſecond point, and prove, that Baptiſme belongs to Children: Firſt, becauſe there was but one Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63260:7"/>ſince the Fall, (which in ſubſtance was Chriſt) though in reſpect of its ſeveral Adminiſtrations called Covenants, as being ſeveral ways adminiſtred; under the Law, by Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion; under the Goſpel, by Baptiſme. Now if God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>Iſraels</hi> Children the prerogative of Circumciſion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, (as was accounted, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4) ſhall we, under the Goſpel, be barred from an anſwerable priviledge in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme? You'l ſay, 'twas no priviledge, read <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. and conſider, <hi>the fooliſhneſſe of God is wiſer then men, and the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God ſtronger then men:</hi> in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.25. <hi>To be a marked ſheep, or Lamb of the flock of Iſrael, is a mercy.</hi> 2. Believers Children are federally holy, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. therefore to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Baptiſme into the Church of Chriſt. 3. Children were baptized in the Cloud and Sea, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2. compared with <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.37. Theſe, the Apoſtle calls Fathers, to the ſucceeding <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> 4. As God owned thoſe Children preſented to him in Circumciſion, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.20, 21. and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them, his Children: So, we believe, he will own ours; eſpecially, conſidering 5. The promiſe to thoſe under the Goſpel, and their Children, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.39. to them believing, and their Children, by vertue of the Parents Faith, (as to <hi>Abraham</hi> believing, and his Seed: for we have but one Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, Chriſt, by whom all are to expect Salvation) and to all afar off, when they believe; and to their Children, by vertue of their Faith; and to as many as God ſhall call to Faith, and to their Children, by vertue of that Faith. Hence the Apoſtle ſayes, <hi>The Promiſe is made to you</hi> (in Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) quoting that Promiſe made to <hi>Adam Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> of Chriſt Jeſus: and ſhall not we and ours par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of it, as well, as <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and their Children? Read <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.17. <hi>We partake of the fat of the Olive tree;</hi> as, thoſe branches of Jews did before their cutting off; but they and their Children did; therefore we, and ours alſo. And here, by the way, obſerve, we plead a Church-priviledge for Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to be, at leaſt in outward Covenant: we ſay not all of them ſhall be ſaved; we uſe the means, and leave the iſſue to God: There are ſome branches ſeemingly in Chriſt, who bring not forth fruit, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.1, 2. yet have the benefit of an external priviledge, as in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mr. Marſhall againſt Mr. Tombs, p <hi>138,</hi>
               </note> In <hi>Mar.</hi> 6.10. <hi>To ſuch
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63260:8"/>belongs the Kingdome of Heaven,</hi> muſt not be interpreted of all Children, (as ſuch) but of Children, whoſe Parents were in the Covenant, as theſe were, and brought by Parents, or neer friends, to Chriſt; <hi>ſuffer ſuch to come to me:</hi> You believe theſe were Children of Jews, yet in Covenant. Now though Chriſt baptized them not, nor any other, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.2. yet he laid his hands on them (A preparative to Baptiſme in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times, if you'l believe Antiquity<note n="†" place="margin">Read Doctor Hammond of baptizing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, p. <hi>194.</hi>
               </note>) and bleſſed them. (If Chriſt gave Children the greater benefit, Bleſſing, why do ye deny them the leſſer, which is Baptiſme?) Now I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you believe it was a ſpiritual bleſſing, being Chriſts gift, for <hi>Eſau</hi> had a temporal and earthly (an heir of the world, as well as <hi>Jacob</hi>) yet he counted himſelf deceived of the bleſſing,<note place="margin">Read my Glim. of Chriſts love, p. <hi>93.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.36, 37, 39. Chriſt alſo affirmed, that to ſuch (Children of Parents in Covenant) belongs the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven: Then deny not Baptiſme to the heirs of heaven.</p>
            <p>But 7. What if <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. make for Infant Baptiſme? though (I wis) you take that Text for your Maſter-piece. <hi>Go, diſcipulize all Nations;</hi> for ſo is the Original. Pray, may not Children be made Diſciples by Baptiſme? read <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. where Chriſt is ſaid to make more Diſciples than <hi>John,</hi> bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing them, intimating the way to make Diſciples, is, to baptize them, and after to teach them, <hi>ver.</hi> 20. Read it carefully, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. So that though ſome ſmall knowledge, and confeſſion, or deſire after Chriſt was required in grown people (none in Children) before Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme: yet moſt teaching, and conſequently knowledge, was afterwards. And hence that paſſage of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 Epiſt. 3.21. is moſt admirably opened by a learned man,<note n="†" place="margin">Dr. Hamond of Infant Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, p. <hi>196.</hi>
               </note> not to be rendred, the Anſwer of a good Conſcience (ſpeaking of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme) but the queſtion, of a good Conſcience toward God; for ſo the Original, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies. For men were diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulized with ſmall quantity of knowledge, and children with none, but taught afterwards, and ſo asked after the things of God, and a good Conſcience after its Baptiſme. Now that Children are accounted Diſciples, read <hi>Act.</hi> 15.5.10. where, when Circumciſion was urged (which was moſt peculiar to Children) <hi>Peter</hi> anſwered [in that moſt famous
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63260:8"/>Council] why put ye a yoke on the Diſciples, meaning on Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, and their Children, under the Goſpel: ſo Children were Diſciples, and may be diſcipulized. You'l ſay, Why were not Children mentioned in the Commiſſion? Anſw. becauſe needleſs: for what was oft mentioned in Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is more ſparingly in the New: Now what more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in Old Teſtament, than to be a God to men, and their Seed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. [if well perpended] and (ye and your Children ſtand before God to make a Covenant, <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.12.) where's a ſpecial command now for Sabbath, except 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1. and that ſo variouſly read by Authors, that it ſeems not clear for that purpoſe? And Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Hiſtory of the Sabbath, part <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>26, 27.</hi>
               </note> brings in many Expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thoſe words; (upon the firſt day of the week. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) occaſioned by the Greek words, which may be rendred, either upon one day of the week, or on the firſt day, or on the Sabbath day (for that day was obſerved, as wel as the Lords day, many years after the Reſurrection;) as Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> obſerves out of <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.10. (an Epiſtle written in the year 59. after Chriſt). And ſo far were the Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans from believing there was a Command to keep holy the firſt day of the week, that after Divine Exerciſes uſed in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall of theirs Saviours Reſurrection, and other bleſſings which befell them that Day, they went to their common work the remainder of the Day: And the learned <hi>Hierom</hi> tells us, that a devout and pious woman, one <hi>Paula,</hi> who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> with certain poor Widows and Virgins privately, after they had been at the Holy Exerciſes of the Congregation one Lords Day, returned home to their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon work,<note n="†" place="margin">Inſtabant operi: et vel ſibi vel aliis veſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta facie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant. See Helyn Hiſt. Sab. part <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>79.</hi>
               </note> which was making cloaths. This I the rather write, to ſhew, that what was commanded oft in Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is ſparingly in the New. Now the Sabbath being mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall (onely the Seventh Day changed into the firſt day of the week) what needed new Commands?</p>
            <p>And ſo for bringing Infants into Covenant in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, We have juſt grounds, having ſo many Commands in the old: if you ſay, that in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1. there is a Command for obſerving the Lords day, becauſe 'tis ſaid, As I have or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained in the Churches of <hi>Galatia.</hi> I anſwer, that relates rather to the collections there mentioned, then to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63260:9"/>a Command for ſetting a part the Lords day: And, in a digreſſion, we have firmer Ordinance for Tythes (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give that Jewiſh expreſſion) in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. Even ſo has God or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) that thoſe that preach the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Tythes in Goſpel time proved.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Apoſtle quotes a former Statute or Ordinance for Miniſtry-maintenance, and that ſeemes out of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, for <hi>v.</hi> 9. the Levitical Text is alledged, thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the Oxe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now never did God appoint any<note n="†" place="margin">Free will-offerings of a atter date.</note> way to maintain thoſe who did his ſervice; but the way of Tythes, which was never type of any thing, nor never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed; and indeed if <hi>Moſes</hi> Prieſthood had a ſet mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, why ſhould our Saviours come ſhort? And the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle pleads a ſet maintenance, Who goes to warre at his own charges, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. have not Souldiers ſet-pay? I could here be large with reaſon, but 'tis a digreſſion. Here is a plainer Ordinance for Tythes, then for the Lords day, yet not looked on. What ſpeciall Command have you for Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens partaking of the Paſcall Lamb, or Lords Supper now? except you court that Text of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. to take your part: Let a man examine himſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and under man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend both ſexes: the words are maſculine (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>): but you'l ſay, The man is a courteous Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature to the woman, and will be content to comprehend her under him. Thus though in expreſſe terms in the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we are not commanded to baptize Children, nor keep Lords day, nor pay Tythes, nor admit Women to the Lords Supper, no nor to ſpeak againſt Uſury, or to hold Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy: yet by good conſequences in the new, &amp; Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands in the old Teſtament, or Rules that look very like Commands. My laſt Argument for Infant-baptiſme, is in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.3. ſince by nature they are Children of wrath; and therefore need Chriſts blood (repreſented in Baptiſme) to waſh away their ſins: The baptizers ſay, the Text calles them Sons of wrath onely, who walked in ſinful and evill courſes; but I anſwer, That Expoſition, gives the Text the lye; for the Apoſtle there plainly ſhews, firſt, the <hi>Epheſians</hi> actuall tranſgreſſions, v. 2. and part of the third; and then their originall ſtate in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of <hi>Adam,</hi> they were by nature Children of wrath (of which more anon). Were not Children, when born, naturall
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63260:9"/>Children? well then by nature Sons of wrath, which made them break forth into ſo many actuall ſins,<note place="margin">Perſon may be loved, and their State hated.</note> of which in v. 2.3. here obſerve, becauſe the <hi>Epheſians</hi> were elect, that their perſons were ever beloved, but their ſtate was the ſtate or condition of wrath, in reſpect of originall ſin; but thus much for Baptiſme of Infants, I could produce more Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and anſwer Objections, but 'tis not my task: there is abundant ſatisfaction to be had in Dr. <hi>Featley,</hi> Mr. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hall,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fuller,</hi> B. D. Dav. <hi>Chytraus de infantum</hi> Bapt. Mr. <hi>Pagit. Roſſaeus,</hi> and others, ſo that Mr. <hi>Fiſhers</hi> vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminous Book (where he calls Baby-Baptiſme Babyiſme) ſhall never prevail with me, to deny Childrens Baptiſm. The third thing you affirmed, was that Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> brought in Baptiſme of Infants; but this is a moſt groſſe error, for <hi>Innocent</hi> the third lived but about the year of our Lord 1198. and brought in Tranſubſtantiation,<note place="margin">Deſcription of <hi>Italy,</hi> pa. 184.</note> and Auricu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar confeſſion (as Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> tells us) but Infant-Baptiſme was in uſe above 1000. years before; but you are not the firſt who have fathered this Infant-Baptiſme upon <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, as you may read in <hi>Pagit</hi> his <hi>Hereſiography,</hi> page 16. Mr. <hi>Marſhall</hi> againſt Mr. <hi>Tombes,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pa. 92.93, 94. &amp;c.</note> has taken pains to prove the Antiquity of Infant-Baptiſme, to have been in the year, 150. after Chriſt, in the dayes of <hi>J. Martyr,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Infant-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme very antient.</note> and produces his Teſtimony for it, which was long before any Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> was in being, and <hi>Origene</hi> who lived not very many years after, affirms Paedobaptiſme to be a tradition received from the Apoſtles, [in whoſe time the word Tradition was uſed in a good ſence, read 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.15.]. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> a Grand Father, who lived in the ſame Century, vvith I.<note place="margin">Page 23.24, 25. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Martyr</hi> confirms Infant-Baptiſme to have been in uſe in his time. You may read Mr. <hi>Marſhall,</hi> vvho vvill alſo give you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count vvhy <hi>Conſtantine, Greg. Nazianzen,</hi> nor <hi>Chryſoſtome, &amp;c.</hi> vvere baptized vvhen Infants, to vvit, becauſe their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents vvere not believers at their births. And having men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned ſome of the Fathers,<note place="margin">Scientia non habet inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum niſi Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantem.</note> I wonder why you ſo ſpeak a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them for darkening the light of the Goſpel. Some of them lived neer the Apoſtles times, ſaw them who heard the Apoſtles, and received light from their light; he that is wiſe will drink as near to the Fountains head as he can,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63260:10"/>becauſe of the pureneſs and clearneſs of the water.<note place="margin">Dulcius ex ipſo ſonte &amp;c. Fideliuns fili ſanctitatis can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didati, &amp; ſancti ex ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis praeroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivâ.</note> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I believe the cauſe why you complain againſt them, is not for want of ignorance of their worth and abilities—. I could produce the teſtimony of <hi>Tertullian</hi> for Infant-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, who lived in the ſame Century with <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> who calles Children holy, in reſpect of their Prerogative in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, to wit, becauſe of believing Parents, and federal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly holy;<note place="margin">Tert. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. de Anima.</note> but I refer the judicious Reader, to Dr. <hi>Hammonds</hi> Treatiſe of baptizing Infants, pag. 213. And I will wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what you ſay concerning <hi>Adam's</hi> ſin.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What puniſhment Adams ſin brought on his Posterity.</head>
               <p>THat <hi>Adam's</hi> ſin brought more on him and his, than temporall death,<note place="margin">Habuit vitam aeternam par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim promiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp; ſpe. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeus in cap. <hi>2.</hi> Gen. p. <hi>348.</hi>
                  </note> with ſorrows, ſickneſſes <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I prove 1. becauſe <hi>Adam</hi> forfeited eternall life, which I thus prove: what the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> reſtored, the firſt loſt; but the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Adam,</hi> reſtored eternall life, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. who brought life and immortality to light, intimating it to have had ſome kinde of being before, to wit, in <hi>Adam</hi> at leaſt, in an incluſive promiſe (in feeding on the Tree of life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) The Tree of life was the repreſenter of eternall life, and of Chriſt Jeſus, the means to bring it about upon the Fall, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.7. Hence <hi>Paraeus,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In Gen.</hi> 1.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Arbor vitae eſt Chriſtus, paradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus terrenus ſymbolum erat caeleſtis gratiae, &amp; ejectio è paradiſo ſignum aeternae abjectionis à Deo, niſifuerit reconciliatus, ibid. Paradiſe</hi> typed out glory the Tree of Life Chriſt, the ejecting man,<note place="margin">Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe.</note> ſignified mans rejection without reconciliation. Hence Dr. <hi>Hall,</hi> O infinite mercy! Man ſaw his Saviour before him, ere he had need of one; he ſaw him in whom he ſhould recover eternall life,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.12. Pag. 130.131. <hi>In Gen. Cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Pag.</hi> 345.</note> ere he loſt it. Now that <hi>Adam</hi> was not promiſed eternall life in Paradiſe, has been the opinion of many: Mr. <hi>Love</hi> thought ſo, Mr. <hi>Wotton</hi> in his Sermons on <hi>John</hi> 1. v. 11. whoſe Arguments prevailed with me, to be once of that judgement. <hi>Paraeus</hi> brings in 7. Arguments to prove,<note place="margin">Et ſanè multis ne contemnen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis rationibus nititur haec ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia. Idem, Ibid.</note> that <hi>Adam</hi> had not promiſe of eternall life in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe,</hi> but refutes them; proving, becauſe we loſt eternal life in him, therefore he had promiſe of it; and the Image of God in him, was the earneſt of it, the Tree of life a <hi>ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolum</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:63260:10"/>of it; and Chriſts reſtoring life proves it loſt in the firſt <hi>Adam.</hi> Here obſerve how differing. Hereticks have been about this matter. <hi>Pelagius</hi> held (and <hi>Socinus</hi> after him) that <hi>Adams</hi> ſin brought onely eternall Death,<note place="margin">Trelcat. de O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig. peccato Pag. <hi>169.</hi>
                  </note> and that tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Death was by nature not the wages of ſin, becauſe not removed by Chriſt. <hi>Pighius</hi> denies any to be guilty of eternall death, till they have actually ſinned, the very Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>George Hammond:</hi> mark how he agrees in part with a Papiſt. Mark how Hereticks diſſent among themſelves; but conſent (as <hi>Pilate</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi>) againſt truth. That place in the <hi>Romans,</hi> Chap. 5.12.14. proves, Death raigned over all who had not ſinned actually as <hi>Adam,</hi> becauſe we all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in <hi>Adam:</hi> of which at large anon. Now Chriſt was to remove onely eternall Death from Elect, and not temporal, onely its bitterneſs. And though it may be objected, that <hi>Adam</hi> had principles of mortality within him, before the Fall, yet he had never died, had he not ſinned, which made <hi>Paraeus</hi> ſay, he was in ſome ſence mortal, in ſome immortal;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 2. <hi>diſtinc:</hi> 19. <hi>p.</hi> 368.</note> and <hi>Lombard</hi> gives the diſtinction how, mortall in reſpect of body,—immortall in reſpect of his Creator (whoſe will it was, had he not ſinned, to have preſerved him from Death, by feeding on the Tree of Life) but after the Fall,<note place="margin">Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe.</note> ſpirituall meat was not fit for a mortall ſtomack, ſayes Dr. <hi>Hall.</hi> But let us conſider the firſt Argument: What Chriſt reſtored, that <hi>Adam</hi> loſt, but Chriſt reſtored eternall life. Hence <hi>Adam</hi> was called the figure or Type of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.14. therefore ſome ſimilitude between <hi>Adam's</hi> loſſe, and Chriſts reſtauration, that as <hi>Adam</hi> loſt eternall life (once) ſo Chriſt reſtored it. This I prove further, becauſe Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment came by one <hi>(viz. Adam)</hi> to condemnation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.16. Here is damnation on all by <hi>Adam,</hi> not onely temporall Death. Now, that condemnation, there, is damnation,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> read the ſame <hi>Greek</hi> word in <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. There is no condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to thoſe that are, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that is, no damnation: read <hi>John</hi> 5.24. This may be proved further, becauſe we were all in <hi>Adam,</hi> Rom. 5.12. and ſinned all in him. Now the grounds are juſt, had <hi>Adam</hi> ſtood, we all had ſtood and lived for ever, therefore ſince he fell, we fell all in him; he being our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative or Parliament (as I may ſay) a common perſon,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63260:11"/>the root of mankind. But you ſay, Our ſouls could not ſin in <hi>Adam,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Page 15.</note> becauſe they were not in him, being not in being. To which I anſwer, We were in him enough to be guilty with him of his Sin. Il'e ſhew you the moſt acute judgements of learned men, on that place of <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. to give ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to any indifferent man; but give me leave a little to play the Scholar with you: were not all ſouls and bodies in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam?</hi> then did not <hi>Adam</hi> beget a perfect or compleat Creature,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.3.</note> as the Beaſts do in their kinde. How did he beget a Son in his own likeneſs, meaning in ſin? was <hi>Adam</hi> onely a body-can a body beget without a ſoul?<note place="margin">Du Moulin ag. Armin. p. <hi>66.</hi> c. 10.</note> was a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full body his likeneſs? can a body be well ſinful without the ſoul? <hi>Adam's</hi> ſoul did firſt ſin; there was the wills conſent, before the hand took the fruit. Sin comes not chiefly by the body,<note place="margin">Magiſter hîc non appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hatur.</note> nor a body can't ſin not beget alone. If <hi>Adam</hi> were onely a body, how got he a Childe in his own likeneſs? Indeed <hi>Peter Lomb. l.</hi> 2. <hi>diſt.</hi> 31. affirms, ſin to be onely from the body; but <hi>Peter Du Moulin,</hi> onely or chiefly from the ſoul; I believe from both in ſome ſort. For the body, who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean?<note place="margin">Creando in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funditur, &amp;c.</note> For the ſoul, it is created (though holy) yet deſtitute of its former Original righteouſneſs, which deficiency to it, is ſin: nay, That we call original.<note place="margin">Ameſius med. Theol. c. <hi>17. Pag. 70</hi>
                  </note> The learned <hi>Ameſs</hi> tells, us, that the want of Original righteouſneſs may be conſidered as a puniſhment, or ſin; As from God a ſoul: is created in the body without it; 'tis a juſt judgement from God; but as that originall righteouſneſs ſhould be in our nature, and is not; <hi>ipſa defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientia eſt animae peccatum,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Read his book pag. 15.</note> That deficiency is ſin. Thus in jeſting with my Antagoniſt, I have almoſt anſwered the Queſtion, unleſs he oppoſe that ſouls are from God, not <hi>Adam, Zach.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Eccleſs.</hi> 12.7. <hi>the ſoul returns to him that gave it.</hi> It may be anſwered, <hi>God gave it,</hi> in giving <hi>Adam</hi> at firſt a power to get it: If that of <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9. where Fathers of fleſh, are oppoſed to Father of ſpirits; and ſo Fathers of fleſh there, are not Fathers of ſpirits; It may be anſwered, that by Father of ſpirits,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Read</hi> Paraeus in Gen. c. <hi>2.</hi> v. <hi>7. p. 338.</hi> &amp; Du Monlin. ag. Ar. <hi>p. 67.</hi>
                  </note> may be underſtood Father of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, becauſe ſanctifying our ſpirits. And we know <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was almoſt of this judgement to his dying day, who was <hi>mallens Hereticorum.</hi> Who doth deſire more ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63260:11"/>faction, let him read the moſt elegant and learned reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Mr. <hi>Nathaniel Culverwel,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 106.</note> in the eleventh Chapter of the light of nature, who would almoſt perſwade, that as <hi>materia oritur ex materiâ</hi> ſo <hi>forma ex formâ,</hi> one ſoul may produce another, one doth print another with the ſame ſtamp of immortality, that it ſelf had engraven firſt upon it: one perſon of the ſacred Trinity produced another; one Candle lights another, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but I forbear,<note place="margin">Heb. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> becauſe my <hi>Pareus</hi> calls it, <hi>bruta &amp; pecuina opinio,</hi> and ſo <hi>Du Moulin.</hi> Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, if any had queſtioned, how an immateriall being had or could have conveyance in a ſeminall way, let them ſhew us the way how 'tis united to the body,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Homer as</hi> Virg. <hi>has it</hi> hominum ſator atque deorum.</note> &amp; we will as eaſily tell them, how it entered into it; but lets not look for ſoul's Parentage on earth, We are of the off-ſpring of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.28. <hi>Prometheus</hi> ſtole fire from Heaven, to quicken bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, as the Poets fabulize.</p>
               <p>Yet we were all in <hi>Adam,</hi> and ſinned in him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. How did <hi>Levi</hi> pay Tithes in <hi>Abraham? Heb.</hi> 7. did his body and not ſoul? juſt ſo, friend <hi>Hammond,</hi> you pay Tithes now, without any conſent of the ſoul: when God ſaid to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, the day (thou) eateſt thou ſhalt die;</hi> ſpake God to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam's</hi> body, without the ſoul?<note place="margin">Omnes erant in Adamo, &amp; pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carunt non actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliter ſedvertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliter incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendo originale peccatum quod iis imputatur is culpam, in quantum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo modo erant in primo paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te &amp; idem cum ipſo, as Dion. Carthaſ in loc. Rom. cap. <hi>5.</hi> on as Lyra <hi>92.</hi> fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura erant membra ipſiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in Rom. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> (I am ſo charitable to your ſelf, friend <hi>Hammond,</hi> to pay for all you will eat, be the meat never ſo coſtly, when your ſoul has left your body) or was ſoul and body both in <hi>Adam,</hi> and forbid eating? ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what God ſpake to <hi>Adam,</hi> he ſpake to all mankind in him, as he ſpake to him: well, he ſinned in ſoul and body, and we in his loyns: therefore his ſin is imputed to our whole man; But mark one hereſie of yours, worſe then that of <hi>Pelagius.</hi> You deny that Children were loſt, or endangered to be eternally loſt in <hi>Adam:</hi> how came they ſaved, what without Chriſt? no, ſure <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12. will deny that; But did Chriſt ſave them? then they were loſt in <hi>Adam;</hi> for he came to ſave what was loſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.11. and that Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpeaks of little Children, verſe 2.3. whom the world offends, verſe 6, I believe in denying Church-priviledges to them. Let your Needle-ſhip well conſider this. <hi>Wollebius</hi> tells us, that <hi>Adam</hi> muſt be conſidered, not as a private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: (ſo you eſteem him, making our ſouls no way en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63260:12"/>in his) but as the Parent,<note place="margin">Perſona Adae infecit naturam &amp; natura per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonas noſtras, <hi>Wolleb.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> head and root of all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind: So what he received for himſelf, and his (as the Image of God, and promiſe of Eternal Life, upon his obedience) he loſt for him, and his,</p>
               <p>But you'l ſay, How were our ſoules in <hi>Adam?</hi> I anſwer with the learned <hi>Trelcatins,</hi> the ſoul is not † out of <hi>Adam,</hi> or we in him,<note place="margin">De Orig. pec. pag. <hi>154.</hi> Trel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat.</note> according to its eſſence, but according to its ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence <hi>ſive</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: for though it be created of God, yet it is not created but in the body, neither has it ſubſiſtence before the body. You'l never be able to deny upon any good grounds, but that we were all in <hi>Adam,</hi> according to what is here ſaid. God promited a ſoul to each one of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> Poſterity, juſt ſuch, as he by obedience, or diſobedience ſhould make them capable of: ſo by vertue of Covenant, or Promiſe, we were all in <hi>Adam;</hi> which Promiſe, might ſome way be included in that Command, <hi>Increaſe and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply.</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Dion Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſian. <hi>in</hi> Rom. 5.12.</note> As many members are in one Body, or Individuals, in one Species, ſo we in <hi>Adam:</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Bulling. <hi>in</hi> Heb. 7.</note> As <hi>Levi</hi> was in <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſo we in <hi>Adam; Levi</hi> was in the Loyns of his Father, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ti in arbore malum nondum enatum,</hi> ſayes <hi>Bullinger;</hi> as an apple in the Tree before Fruit-time. And ſo was our Saviour, both in <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Abraham:</hi> In <hi>Adam,</hi> the Nature ſinned which he took,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>In</hi> Heb. 7. <hi>ver.</hi> 10. Joh. Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dati.</note> but it was not ſinfull in his perſon, becauſe conceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Holy Ghoſt: In <hi>Abraham,</hi> Chriſt in his ſervant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like condition may be ſaid to have paid Tythes to <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zedeck,</hi> the type of himſelf; though the learned <hi>Diodate</hi> thinks, Chriſt was not to be comprehended amongſt the Tithe-payers (though in <hi>Abrahams</hi> Loyns) becauſe as Son of God he was Prieſt, in whom his humane nature ſubſiſted. The ſame Author tells us,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>In</hi> Rom. 5.12.</note> All were in <hi>Adam,</hi> as in the main ſtock of all Generation, being the head and root of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. And the <hi>Aſſemb. Annot.</hi> uſe the ſame words on that place.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>In</hi> Gen. 2. <hi>&amp; pag.</hi> 409.</note> 
                  <hi>Paraeus</hi> ſayes, we were all in <hi>Adams</hi> loyns, as part of him, and ſo his ſinne was properly ours. The <hi>Syriac</hi> tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of <hi>Tremellius</hi> reads it, <hi>By the hand of one man ſinne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred</hi>— as if;<note place="margin">Totus homo to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum hominem naturaliter fundit: nec eſt peccatum materiae out partis hominis, ſed totius ſuppoſiti: homo generans communicat, quod materiale materialiter, quod immateriale cauſa liter. lucas. <hi>Trel. pag. 153.</hi>
                  </note> when <hi>Adam</hi> took of the fruit, we all ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63260:12"/>out our hands in his, and are when he are.<note n="†" place="margin">Coucludimus nec in ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtià animae out carmis hanc contagionem habcre cauſam: ſed quia a Deo fuit ordinatum <hi>&amp;c.</hi> vide <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin,</hi> niſt. <hi>l. 2. c. 1.</hi>
                  </note> A learned Proteſtant Divine tells us that the whole man begets the whole man naturally: the materiall part he begets mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially; the immateriall cauſally, as being the cauſe of it's ſubſiſtence in the body. And <hi>Gorrhanus</hi> expounding how we were in <hi>Adam,</hi> ſayes, we were in <hi>Adam,</hi> as in the matter not onely ſinning by <hi>Adams</hi> example (as the Pelagians af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm) but we were in him, as in the cauſe, becauſe his ſinne was the cauſe of ours. <hi>Gorrhanus</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. The <hi>Greck</hi> words may be read two wayes, either, By one mans offence ſinne entred into the world, and Death by ſinne, becauſe all ſinned: ſo the <hi>Syriac</hi> tranſlation: and <hi>Bulliger,</hi> expounding it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for this cauſe: or elſe in whom all ſinned, we being all le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally in <hi>Adam,</hi> and by way of Equity and Juſtice, to ſtand and fall with him. And thus your Expoſition of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 5. <hi>(In ſinne I was conceived)</hi> falls to the ground, without any fur ther Anſwer. For if <hi>David</hi> vvere conceived in ſinne, there muſt be ſoul as well as body: Now the ſoul wants its original righteouſneſs, to guide and direct it, out of a juſt Judgment from God; which want to it, is ſinne beſides the bodies ſtains. So that what other Expoſitions you make on the Text, (which I ſhall not trouble the Reader with) are yours, not <hi>Davids,</hi> and ſit beſide the ſaddle. How <hi>David's,</hi> or any ones ſoul and body meet and work in the † contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinne, I willingly paſs by, and come to your obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction out of <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. <hi>The Son ſhall-not die for the Father:</hi> Which falls to the ground by what has been ſaid. I yield, An innocent Son ſhal not die for the Fathers ſinne (as that Chapter means) but <hi>Adam's</hi> Sons were not ſuch: in him we all ſinned, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. As really as <hi>Levi</hi> paid Tythes in <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham's</hi> Loyns, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7, But 2ly, that Chapter in <hi>Ezek.</hi> ſpeaks onely of actual ſins, not ſuch as we have from <hi>Adam;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it proves nothing to purpoſe.</p>
               <p>You draw an Argument againſt Childrens being defiled, (and that therefore they need not Baptiſme, nor were cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted in <hi>Adam</hi> in the inward man) <hi>No defiled Creature can enter into Heaven;</hi> but children are fit for the Kingdom of Heaven, therefore not defiled. Magiſterially delivered Anſw. The Kingdom of Heaven is to be taken two wayes,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63260:13"/>and Children to be looked upon under a two-fold conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<list>
                     <item>1. The Kingdome of Heaven is to be taken for the Kingdom of Grace, according to <hi>Mar.</hi> 9.1. and ſo in <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.12. Some were there ſtanding, who taſted not Death, till the Kingdome of God came with power; till Chriſt owned, Churches gathered, Ordinances adminiſtred: Now Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of believing Parents, belong to this Kingdome, and it to them, though ſuch as you bar them from the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Kingdom of Grace.</item>
                     <item>2. The Kingdom of Heaven is taken for glory, and no children fit for it, being all natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally defiled, and children of wrath.</item>
                  </list>
Now conſider Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens natural condition and they are defiled,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Praeparavit, <hi>ſayes</hi> Beza, <hi>in</hi> Rom. 9.23. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Idoneos licet non dignos fecit, <hi>Col. 1.</hi>
                  </note> and their ſtate a condition of wrath, But again, conſider them as Elected and in the Eternal Covenant with God in Chriſt, and ſo all the perſons of Election were ever beloved, and fitred for Heaven, by Juſtification, and Sanctification. That all veſſels of mercy, are fitted or prepared for glory: Read <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.23. and Col. 1.12. Now I ask the queſtion, Were children veſſels of mercy, or no? I am ſure, you'r ſay, yes: Firſt, then, they were loſt in <hi>Adam,</hi> and in miſery (for mercy preſuppoſeth miſery.) And 2. then they muſt be fitted for glory, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not naturally fit. Dr. <hi>Uſher</hi> tells us largely, in his book called, <hi>The Sum and Subſtance of Chriſtian Religion,</hi> pag. 416. How Children, by Sanctification, are fitted for glory; and though by reaſon of ignorance, and tender youth, they are not capable of juſtification, as to underſtand it, yet they have nefit of that Eternall and Immanent act of God in Chriſt Jeſus, in which he imputed their ſins to Chriſt, and his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe to them, though the tranſient act were not percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by them: Read Dr. <hi>Kendal</hi> againſt <hi>Goodwins Redemption redeemed,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">In his moſt learned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi> Pag. 17, 18.</note> who will tell you, That if God did not ſome way act in Juſtification from Eternity, then God doth ſomething in time, not formerly decreed, which argues ſome change in God. But I proceed, to examine your mind about <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Jacob:</hi> You conceive no Text proves <hi>Eſau's</hi> Reprobatior before born. I could produce the judgment of above a hundred famous Writers affirming it,<note place="margin">Read Prov. 16. ver. 4.</note> but I'le come to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and argue thus: If God did not hate <hi>Eſau</hi> before he was born, but after; then he loved him before he was born, but
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63260:13"/>he loved him not; becauſe,
<list>
                     <item>(1.) that would argue a change in God to love and hate the ſame perſon.</item>
                     <item>2. The 9. of <hi>Rom.</hi> ſayes, God had a purpoſe about them before they were born, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. Was that purpoſe to love <hi>Eſau,</hi> or hate him? If he love him, how could he, without change, hate him? I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive God after hated him: therefore, in all likelyhood, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was born: for Gods Decrees are poſitive and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changable; he calls the things that are not, as if they were, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.17. He ſaw him condemned, before born; for Gods Decrees depend not upon man.</item>
                     <item>3. How comes <hi>Malachy</hi> to quote that place of <hi>Gen.</hi> 25. and, <hi>Paul</hi> to quote both, if not to one purpoſe? 'twas declared,<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> (As) notes the likeneſs and coherency of the Texts.</note> the Elder ſhould ſerve the Younger, before they were born; and St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, † <hi>As it was written, Jacob have I loved:</hi> To wit, before-born: And <hi>Eſau</hi> have I hared; to wit, before-born.</item>
                  </list>
Or how comes elſe the Apoſtle to quote ſeveral Texts, if not one to explain another? Sure, none put an old piece to a new gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or parallel texts where no agreement is. Pray, doth not the effect prove the ſame? Why found he no place in God, nor father, (to change his mind, after giving away the Bleſsing) nor in himſelf for Repentance, if not reprobated? And was not his ſervitude fore-told before born, a token of hatted? and <hi>Jacobs</hi> priviledge of Maſtery over his Brother, fore-told, beforeborn, and evident ſign of love? I could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to enlarge my ſelf on this ſubject, but I muſt ſtudy to be brief. You alleadge, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.11. <hi>that God deſires not the death of ſinners.</hi> Anſw. I confeſs,<note place="margin">Voluntas ſigui non beneplaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li.</note> God deſires not the ruine of any ſinner who can repent; <hi>Eſau</hi> could not to any pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. which was a ſign of Rejection: For if Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving be a ſign of Election, (as 'tis <hi>Act.</hi> 13.48.) then Unbelief and Non-penitency is a ſign of Reprobation. God onely can give Repentance, in a <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. But, ſecondly, were theſe ſuch wicked as <hi>Eſau?</hi> Then I deny, that God ever intended them repentance more then to <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon, Matth.</hi> 11. 21. but men utterly appointed to deſtruction, as <hi>Benhadad</hi> in the Letter, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 20.42. and fore-ordained to Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>Jude</hi> 4. For God deſires Juſtice to be done to the Wicked. 3. Were not theſe Elected, but Wicked, while in their ſins, whoſe ruine God would not have? But 4. this
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63260:14"/>expreſſion ſhews Gods revealed Will, (if he ſpake to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates) to make them ſome way unexcuſable; not his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed, or decretal will: of which anon. But you preſſe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. God would have all to be ſaved. Pray conſider, how the Apoſtle commands to pray for Kings there, and gives that Reaſon, becauſe he would have all, <hi>i. e.</hi> all ſorts of men to be ſaved; though Kings then did perſecute Gods people much: And to that place, in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. I anſwer, the Apoſtle ſpeaks of the Saints and Beloved, <hi>v.</hi> 1. and tells them, Why God was ſo ſlack in coming to judge Wicked: Why ſo patient, &amp;c. that Gods long-ſuffering was to Us<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward (not the Wicked) <hi>ver. 9.</hi> Not willing that any; to wit, of us, the Elect ſhould periſh &amp;c. Pray, what have you got by theſe Texts though you brag of your acquaintance in Script; ob-rading Mr. <hi>Rutton,</hi> for not exerciſing therein, and for mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes: Though I am confident,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 19.</note> he is more apound Bible, them thouſands of ſuch as you. You proceed, and would prove that <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. <hi>[Has not the Potter power over the Clay?—]</hi> will prove nothing to our purpoſe; but would make the Apoſtle quote it out of <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.6. Which Texts are not a like, nor have any agreement: for that of <hi>Jeremy</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means, Firſt, that the Potters work was <hi>Adam,</hi> and we in him: Secondly, <hi>Adam's</hi> marring, and we in him: Or elſe it means, 1. Gods work, in making them a people, Church, or State. 2ly, Their marring by diſobedience, &amp;c. But could ought be marred in Gods hand, againſt his will? Was he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of his work, or in it, as the Potter. Was <hi>Adam</hi> loſt, or <hi>Iſrael</hi> ruined without God? and yet God is moſt holy, juſt, and good the Evil from Man: the over-ruling from God. (Read my Comment upon <hi>Rev.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 135.</note> 
                  <hi>chap.</hi> 17. <hi>v.</hi> 17. how God put it into the hearts of the Kings: how the matter of an action is from God: how the formality, or the obliquity is from man &amp;c.) What made the Potter go about to make a veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of honour, was it any worth in the clay? Was it deſert in <hi>Iſrael</hi> cauſed God to make them a people? Or do you believe Election, and an Eternal Boſome of Love in God the Father? Was it not want of power made the Potter marre his Veſſel? And doth God lack power<note n="†" place="margin">Read <hi>Eſay 43.13.</hi> I will work, and who can hinder?</note> to ſave thoſe who are loſt? Could he have done no more to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63260:14"/>
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 5? Then he muſt ceaſe to be omnipotent, and ceaſe to be God. He did enough to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to make them inex cuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: He had power enough to ſave all the world, had he not otherwiſe decreed. But examine carefully, and you will find more in <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. then in <hi>Jer.</hi> 18. The former, pleads Gods Prerogative-Royall over all Creatures, making them ſuch as he pleaſes, rejecting <hi>Pharoah, Eſau,</hi> the Jews,<note place="margin">Read Prov. 16.4. Exod. 9.16. Rom. 9.22.</note> though murmuring at it, <hi>ver.</hi> 19, 20. with that Expoſtulation, <hi>Has not the Potter power over the Clay?</hi> The latter, means <hi>Iſraels</hi> marring in Captivity, being firſt marred with ſinfulneſs, Examine <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. and <hi>Jer.</hi> 18. and they will ſhew your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake: For in <hi>Jer.</hi> the ſame Veſſel is made; and being mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, is re-made into another form: But in <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. the Potter is ſaid to have power, out of the ſame lump, to make one veſſel to honour, and (another) to diſhonour, as in <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſan:</hi> Pray, what agreement is here? Do not Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates murmure, <hi>ver.</hi> 19. ſaying, <hi>Why haſt thou made us ſo?</hi> We were caſt in <hi>Adam,</hi> and reſiſted not thy Will, till actuall tranſgreſſion, before which we were caſt: And why doth God yet find fault with us, ſince caſt in <hi>Adam?</hi> To which the Apoſtle anſwers out of Gods Prerogative,<note place="margin">Sodom now ſuffering pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment in Hell ſire.</note> 
                  <hi>Has not GOD (as well as a Potter) power over the clay of the ſame lump, (ſo we were in</hi> Adam) <hi>to make one veſſel to honour,</hi> &amp;c.) Thus your Argument is marred in your hand, againſt your Will, as the Veſſel in <hi>Jeremies</hi> Potter. I have ſaid enough in anſwert to <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.20. already. We cannot make out ſelves Veſſels of mercy, if once our perſons were made veſſels of wrath. There is a great gulf fixed, <hi>Luk,</hi> 16. They are by God before prepared for glory, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.23. who are veſſels of mercy; onely man muſt co-work. Your Expoſition of <hi>Sodoms</hi> ſuffering, will ſuffer much upon Examination. You dany the <hi>Sodomites</hi> to be in Hell, and that fire was called Eternal, becauſe from Heaven, not kindled by man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer,</hi> You almoſt deny, or give the Scripture the Lye: for <hi>Jud.</hi> 7. tells, that <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha</hi> are (ſuffering) the vengeance of Eternal Fire, that is, now in miſety. Now the former fire is<note n="†" place="margin">Sol in Pol Hiſt. ca. <hi>48.</hi>
                  </note> out, which deſtroyed their bodies (for a great Lake called the <hi>Aſphaltite,</hi> in the vacancy of Inhabitants, has taken poſſeſſion of that Plain, where <hi>Sodom,</hi> &amp;c. ſtood)
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63260:15"/>Read Mr. <hi>Fullers Pisgah-ſight of Palestine.</hi> So, the fire in which the <hi>Sodomites</hi> ſuffer now,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 13. <hi>p.</hi> 270.</note> is Hell. <hi>Jude</hi> (in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability) took part of his Epiſtle, our of the ſecond Epiſtle of <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6. (Read Mr. <hi>Fran. Roberts,</hi> on <hi>Jude.</hi>) Though you 06 would not have one man borrow of another,<note place="margin">Key of Bible.</note> (pag. 69.) where <hi>Peter</hi> tells how the caſes, or bodies, were deſtroyed: but <hi>Jude</hi> tells us of their now ſuffering; therefore the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els are by the Devill burning in Hell.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Apriori, <hi>or</hi> apoſteriori.</note> I could laugh, and tell you, that if <hi>Sodom's</hi> fire were Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, it muſt be Eternal as God is, and then ſome Creature coeternal with the Creator, or to laſt for ever, and then Hell-fire and it will be kin to each other.</p>
               <p>Now if the Devil actually ſuffers in Hell, the <hi>Sodom,</hi> as it is plain in <hi>Jude</hi> 5.6.<note place="margin">The Devill ſuffering in Hell.</note> 
                  <hi>The Angles which kept not their firſt habitation, even as</hi> Sodom, <hi>ſuffering the vengeance,</hi> &amp;c. But you deny the Devil yet ſuffers, <hi>p.</hi> 28. Read 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4. <hi>If God ſpared not the Angels that ſinned, but caſt them down to hell,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. What plainer? Now if Devils in Hell, then <hi>Sodomites,</hi> (for <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Jude</hi> parallel them) then chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, then they deſerved damnation in <hi>Adam.</hi> That Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſuffer, we believe, becauſe all in <hi>Sodom</hi> ſuffered, in which were Women and Children (young and old, ſayes <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.4.) And <hi>John</hi> ſaw ſuch, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12. ſmall and great ſtand before God ready to be judged, therefore ſuch are guilty.</p>
               <p>But you deny any ſoul yet in glory:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 34.</note> What means <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13. <hi>Bleſſed from henceforth are the dead?</hi> And <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.43. <hi>This day thou ſhalt be with me in Paradiſe.</hi> If you ſay, a day with the Lord is as a thouſand years, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, Chriſt meant it of a Natural Day:<note place="margin">Saints now in glory.</note> As <hi>Jonah</hi> was in 06 the belly of the Whale three dayes; ſo the Son of Man in the Earth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.4. And one of thoſe ſay, that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe is not heaven: Read 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.2-4. and be ſatisfied. For what the Apoſtle calls Heaven, v. 2. he calls Paradiſe v. 4. Now the Objections brought againſt Satans being in Hell, may be thus anſwered: though the fulneſs of torment be not till hereafter, when Chriſt ſhall take full vengeance, as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63260:15"/>2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7, 8. &amp; <hi>Jude</hi> 14. may be underſtood, yet the damned ſuffer in part, as is proved. You object <hi>Matth.</hi> 8. Why, art thou come to torment us before the time? Anſw. They knew not how ſoon the day of judgement would come, and deſired liberty to ſin till then, then they knew they ſhould be in full miſery, 'twas recreation to them, to do hurt to poor Creatures, Chriſts miracles and preaching diſpoffeſſed them, and troubled or tormented them. Hell is the place of wicked, hence <hi>Judas</hi> went to his proper place, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.25. Tell me, where are all the ſouls of Saints and wicked de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted? <hi>Revel.</hi> 6.10. ſayes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.3.</note> the Saints ſoules were under the Altar, Chriſt; therefore in bliſſe. Chriſt ſayes, All are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live to God, <hi>Luke</hi> 20.38. therefore all Saints happy. But you ſay, the Devill is Prince of the Air, therefore not yet in torment: beſides, Earth ſhall be Hell, <hi>Iſay</hi> 24. Anſw. though he exerciſe, under God, ſome Authority, yet he is in ſome torment, as is proved, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4. 'tis ſome pleaſure to do hurt, hencethey beg not to be diſpoſſeſſed, <hi>Mar.</hi> 1.24. chap. 5.7. freedom and liberty from Hell is ſome pleaſure:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Hence they plead not to be caſt into Hell, <hi>Luke</hi> 8.31. with we render by, into the deep, which is Hell; for if by Deep, Hell were not meant,<note place="margin">Read <hi>Paſor</hi> on that word.</note> the Devills fooliſhly begged not to go in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the deep, v. 31. and yet deſired to enter into the Swine, and run into the Sea, v. 32.33. You affirm, Hell will be in Earth, therefore none for the preſent. Your proof is in <hi>Iſay</hi> 24:21. God will puniſh the Kings of the Earth, in the Earth, or on it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Pray, what Kings of the Earth have not been puniſhed by Gods hand, ſome by <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> they by <hi>Babylonians,</hi> they by <hi>Perſians,</hi> they by <hi>Grecians, &amp;c.</hi> here on earth? then Hell is paſt, if the Text meant it. 2. High ones were puniſhed, <hi>i. c.</hi> Emperours,<note place="margin">Iſay <hi>24.21.</hi> opened and cleared.</note> Monarchs and petty Princes under them, whoſe Thrones were, as it were on earth, in reſpect of them, whoſe Throne was among the Starres (in conceit) <hi>Iſay</hi> 14.13. But it this place meant Hell, how could they be viſited again, as v. 22. ſhould their viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation be for better or worſe? if for better, here's good news for damned: if for worſe, pray what can be worſe then Hell, eſpecially if men be in full torment; as you mean
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63260:16"/>by this place, applying it after the day of judgement; but in brief, God puniſhed Kings, but viſited them again in temporalls, or their fucceſſors and Nations, with the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of peace, in reſpect of whoſe glory, Sun and Moon were dim, when Chriſt (by aſcenſion and ſending the ſpirit, garther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Churches) raigned before <hi>Iſrael</hi> gloriouſly. In my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, when you ſay, Hell ſhall be on earth, and that darkneſs, no Sun nor Moon: you oppoſe your Tenet of the reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Creation. In concluſion of your examination of Mr. <hi>Ruttons</hi> letter, you ſay he asked you for a ſign of your Miniſtry.<note place="margin">Sed cum nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum fecil, ipſe ſuit miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum.</note> You tell us, An adulterous Generation ſeeks for a ſigne. <hi>John</hi> came with no miracle, yet acknowledged for a true Teacher of Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 10.41. but I anſwer, if you have no more to plead for your being a Miniſter of Chriſt, then this lying book, you may read your doom in <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.23. <hi>Go, I know you not.</hi> And thus much for your Examination of Mr. <hi>Ruttons</hi> letter.<note place="margin">God decreed not <hi>Adams</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ruine, and all his, upon his fall unevitably.</note> You further argue. That if <hi>Adam</hi> had decreed againſt him eternall Death, and all in his loins up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his diſobedience, and that not inflicted on them, then is God changeable, according to thoſe that maintain that te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, To decree a thing, and alter it argues a change; but God changes not: therefore.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> God never decreed, that <hi>Adam</hi> and all his ſhould eternally periſh, God decreed to ſend Chriſt: therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed not to eternally ruine <hi>Adam</hi> and his Poſterity, which I prove thus. If God decreed not to ſend Chriſt to redeem man (foreſeeing the fall) and that from eternity, then God did ſomewhat about Chriſt and mans ſalvation, not former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly decreed,<note place="margin">Cauſa tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſionis Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi nec Deus nec decretum: <hi>92.</hi> interdixit ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini à fructu &amp; decretum non impellebat ad peccandum Wolleb. cap. <hi>9.</hi> &amp; Canon. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> or decreed in time (a ſtrange and unheard of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of God:) the ſame may be ſaid of <hi>Adam's</hi> fall: was it decreed or not? If <hi>Adam's</hi> fall decreed (and God no way guilty) and Chriſts comming into the world, then not <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam's</hi> eternall inevitable ruine, becauſe theſe are contrary; but theſe two laſt were decreed, <hi>Adam's</hi> fall and Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to redeem man. So that though <hi>Adam</hi> were inveſted with right to eternall life, and forfeited it for him and his, yet Chriſt was partly in that decree, to bring all about again for Gods glory; and ſo no change in God; or plainer, God did not ſo inevitably decree <hi>Adam's</hi> ruine eternally, but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63260:16"/>that Chriſt was in that decree, to bring life and immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to light through the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Now obſerve, Gods outward will is not alwayes, nay ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, his decree: though he threatned <hi>Adam,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Lomb. Lib. <hi>1.</hi> &amp; Diſtinc. <hi>45.</hi> of Gods will, or Petrus Aquila. in <hi>46.</hi> of Scocus deſtinc.</note> he had not decreed inevitably his ruine. All School men allow of a concealed and revealed will (if I could render the words ſo, <hi>volunt s ſigui &amp; beneplaciti</hi>) the former is unchangeable, not the latter. In the latter are 1. his threatnings (as to <hi>Adam, Hezekiah,</hi> and <hi>Ninive</hi>) 2. Commands as to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> to let <hi>Iſrael</hi> go, and to <hi>Abraham,</hi> to ſacriſice his Son, &amp;c. here God changed his ſentence, not his decretall will, which is moſt one and unchangeable. <hi>Du. Moulin</hi> likes not this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinction, but Dr. <hi>Kendall</hi> maintains it; For plainer and for further ſatisfaction, read my Glimps of Chriſtian love, page 21.22. and come to the ſecond Argument, wherein you ſay, that <hi>Adam's</hi> ſin was onely againſt the firſt Covenant, (which is true) and in your third Argument, that all his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments were onely earthly: now ſay you, the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the firſt Covenant was onely temporall death, &amp;c. and the ſin againſt the ſecond Covenant, onely, did deſerve damnation in Hell: now Children in <hi>Adam</hi> ſinned, but the firſt way, againſt the firſt Covenant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> All in <hi>Adam</hi> ſinned unto condemnation,<note place="margin">Breach of fir covenant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not onel a temporall Death.</note> or dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18. as is proved largely already, all being in his loyns, as before is maintained: if Children ſinned onely againſt the firſt Covenant, (in your ſence) how are they Children of wrath by nature, as is expounded before? how came they to enjoy Heaven? by Chriſt, or not? if by Chriſt, then they were loſt, as if they had been in the ſecond Covenant: if ſome go to Heaven without Chriſt, what means <hi>Acts</hi> 4. no other name men have to be ſaved by, but by the name of Jeſus. Now though <hi>Adam's</hi> enjoyments are named moſt as earthly, did they not ſignifie, heavenly to be enjoyed upon obedience? was not <hi>Paradiſe</hi> a Type of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? What meant Tree of Life, but eternall life? <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.7. why was he not endued onely with an earthly ſoul? or what needed an immortall ſoul for onely earthly enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? You do not wiſely look unto the end and meaning of theſe things; but as the Jews on their ſacrifices: or, art
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63260:17"/>willingly ignorant, as in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.5. which is worſe. I paſſe by your Expoſition of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. what though Chriſt was the quickener after <hi>Adam's</hi> fall, and beyond <hi>Adam?</hi> was not <hi>Adam</hi> inveſted with an immortall ſoul? was he not ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to the earthly condition of Beaſts? had he not a <hi>poſſe non mori?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> what means that Text, <hi>in dying, thou ſhalt die?</hi> as the <hi>Hebrew</hi> has it, but in dying temporally, thou ſhalt die eternally, (according to Gods revealed will.) Read my Glimps, how many Deaths, p. 29. But ſuppoſe it but an <hi>Hebrew</hi> expreſſion;<note place="margin">Wolleb. lib. <hi>1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.12.</hi>
                  </note> yet under Death, all mans miſery is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained as Death ſpirituall, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. I know thy works, and that thou haſt a name that thou art alive; but thou art dead, 2. the death of afflictions, as <hi>Exod.</hi> 10. Intreat the Lord, that he remove from me this death. 3. Death temporall, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhall return to duſt, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.4. eternall death, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. called the ſecond death; but I attend what you ſay in your fifth Argument, where you argue thus, That opinion wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h makes God a lyar, and the Devill tell true, is to be rejected; but that Opinion which holds, that <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould die more then a temporall death, is ſuch; for <hi>Adam's</hi> Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity are not in Hell, onely die temporally, and Satan told them, ye ſhall not die, &amp;c. but God ſaid, ye ſhall ſurely die: therefore <hi>Adam</hi> was onely threatned with temporall death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Your <hi>Minor</hi> is falſe; for though God threatned <hi>Adam</hi> with eternall Death, yet he lyed not, in not inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, becauſe his threatning was to deterr <hi>Adam</hi> from ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and not Gods peremptory reſolution, but as to <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> and <hi>Niniveh;</hi> for God had decreed before the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Elect in <hi>Adam,</hi> by Chriſt Jeſus: therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended not their ruine; but of this already. Gods ſentence was for Death, not his decree, except for Reprobates; but you that can excuſe the Devill, and accuſe God, according to this judgement: how did the Devill ſay true, do not men die temporally and eternally for firſt ſin? By one mans of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence judgment came upon all to condemnation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18. as the free gift in Chriſt Jeſus, was to juſtification. Either ſay, Chriſt brought not juſtification to life by his obedience, or elſe conclude, <hi>Adam</hi> brought eternal condemnation (on
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63260:17"/>non-Elect) by diſobedience, or elſe ſay, there is no ſence in the Apoſtles arguing, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18. all were condemned to die temporally the day <hi>Adam</hi> ſinned, but were repliev'd to increaſe the world: ſo all the Reprobates were condemned in <hi>Adam</hi> (fore ordained to condemnation in <hi>Jude</hi>) but judgement deferred for many Reaſons, not remitted. Your ſixth Argument is already anſwered, that tho Children bring into the world ſuch ſins, as make them liable to the ſecond death, yet they may belong to Heaven, as I have ſhewed: the perſon of an Elect Veſſel may be loved, ſanctified in time—though the naturall condition were hated. And it were ſad for Children, if not naturally Children of wrath and loſt, or elſe have no Saviour, if no ſin,<note place="margin">Matth. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> not are to be found, if not loſt. To ſuch the Kingdom of grace belongs, by vertue of Parents faith. How prove you, that their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents or friends that brought them, had not faith? they were Sons of Jews yet in Covenant, who had a good opinion of our Saviour, and in all likelihood, brought them for a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall end; or elſe how did Chriſt anſwer their expectation, in bleſſing them? You ſay <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. is not underſtood of Children in Age. What think you of verſ. 2.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>—</note> Jeſus called a little Childe? what think you of his placing him (which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timates the Childs youth and ignorance) from which Childe Chriſt ſayes, men muſt be converted as Children. Goe then 1. Children are ſubjects of ſanctification (which is part of converſion) or elſe go not to Heaven, becauſe fleſh and blood cannot, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. (2.) have faith, though not actually, yet the ſeeds and habit of faith, which will appear in time. (3.) may be offended, or you an offence to them, in denying them admittance into the Kingdom of grace by baptiſme.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:63260:18"/>
            <head>Of the Lawfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry.</head>
            <p>ANd thus much of your Treatiſe of Originall Sin. I come briefly to your Characters of Miniſters: and ſhall tell you, that it would be too great an honour to you, to anſwer you at large in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; and it were to confeſs ſome guiltineſs in our Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: Yet had you queſtioned our Office, or our Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or our coming through the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I would have endeavoured to ſatisfie any ordinary man therein; and a word anon of it. However, I remember when <hi>Scaliger</hi> that proud Critick, had abuſed the noble <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> tells him,<note place="margin">Deſcription of Prit. p. <hi>468.</hi>
               </note> (as I can tell you) <hi>A Fools bolt is ſoon ſhot;</hi> and quotes <hi>Socrates</hi> Reſolution, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>If an Aſs</hi> (excuſe the expreſſion) <hi>kick us, we muſt not put him in the Court;</hi> the beſt is, <hi>Many ſhoulders will make the burden light.</hi> You endeavour to diſgrace all Miniſters, 'tis thought your mouth is no ſlander;<note place="margin">L. <hi>10.</hi> &amp; Ep. <hi>82.</hi>
               </note> ſuch wounds, are our glory. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> his Obſervation upon <hi>Iſraels</hi> diſowning the Prophet <hi>Elias,</hi> is ſeaſonable <hi>Corvi agnoſcebant prophetam Domini quem Judei non agnoſcebant,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>paſcebant corvi quem genus illud per ſequebatur.</hi> The Ravens owned him for a Prophet of the Lord, whom the Jews diſowned; and fed him, whom thoſe people perſecuted.</p>
            <p>Is not our Ordination good? We had impoſition of hands by the Miniſtry, as <hi>Timothy</hi> (in ſome way) had. You'l ſay, Then the Spirit was given by Impoſition.— Pray ſhew me a Reaſon, why we may not uſe the Ceremony, and hope for a bleſſing? Is not the weakneſs of God ſtronger then man? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.25. And that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>fooliſhneſs of God wiſer then men?</hi> You'l ſay, We are ordained without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of People: I muſt tell you, that <hi>Titus</hi> (in all likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood) did ſo. <hi>Paul</hi> left him in <hi>Crete,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain Elders in every City, as <hi>Paul</hi> appointed. Now I know
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63260:18"/>no other Appointment, but by Impoſition of hands: The people could not make them Miniſters themſelves, or by their choice; for then what need had <hi>Paul</hi> to have left <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> there? Again, the word implyes, that the power was in <hi>Titus:</hi> and ſo the ſame word is uſed, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.10. The King of <hi>Egypt</hi> did appoint <hi>Joſeph</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſame word) Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Egypt,</hi> where, I hope, the power was conceived to be in the King, not People: Which paſſage, <hi>Philo Judens</hi> renders by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. As Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> quotes him; intimating the power (as the Greek words uſed for Impoſition of hands, or Setting apart,<note place="margin">Concerning Ordination, pag. <hi>314.</hi>
               </note> imply) to be in <hi>Titus,</hi> and the <hi>Preſbytery,</hi> not People: though I ſhould conſent to the Peoples approbation, could it well be obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. You'l ſay, our Miniſtry came from <hi>Rome.</hi> I anſwer, Suppoſe once Popery crept into <hi>England,</hi> have we not ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from all their Ceremonies, and keep cloſe to the <hi>word,</hi> and ſhall we not be accepted? Or, could their Ceremony ſpoyl the ſubſtance? But I deny that we are of <hi>Rome,</hi> onely were in <hi>Rome,</hi> or came through it. And came not Chriſt from <hi>Adam</hi> through ſinfull Loyns, and yet the true Chriſt? Did not <hi>Aarons</hi> Prieſthood ſucceſſively come to our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours time <hi>(ſed quare)</hi> through ſinful men, and yet owned by our Saviour? the Prieſthood, not the Perſons, who cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified him. And may not a Prieſthood come undefiled through <hi>Rome,</hi> for matter of ſubſtance? But I'le prove we were Chriſtians in <hi>England,</hi> and had Miniſters before <hi>Romes</hi> Apoſtacies many years.</p>
            <p>Our Hiſtories make manifeſt,<note place="margin">The Brittiſh Church, Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent from <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>Auguſtine</hi> the Monk was ſo far from being the firſt Planter of Chriſtianity here, that he found Brit. Biſhops, who did deny obedience to the Chu. of <hi>Rome,</hi> as appears by the B. of <hi>Bangors</hi> Letter, to <hi>Aug.</hi> the Monk, deſiring his ſubjection to the <hi>Romane</hi> Church. <hi>Notum ſit vobis,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Nos eſſe ſub gubernatione Epiſcopt Caerlegionis ſuper Oſca,</hi> &amp;c. And before, Sir <hi>Hen. Spelman,</hi> out of the Annals of <hi>Gisburn</hi> cites, thus:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Concil. Anglic.</hi> p. 188. and p. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Aburbe legionum Meneviam tranſlata ſedes Metropolitana tempore</hi> S. David <hi>Epiſcopiper Arthurum,</hi> from <hi>Caerlyon</hi> upon <hi>Oske</hi> the Metropolitan Seat was tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to St. <hi>Davids,</hi> by King <hi>Arihur,</hi> in the time when St. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> was Biſhop, where there ſtood 13 chief Biſhops,—
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63260:19"/>where Conſecration was, without making any ſubjection to any other Church. And <hi>Lanfrank,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> under <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour, refuſed to be ſubject to <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the 7.<note place="margin">of Feſtivals of the <hi>Church,</hi> pag. 419.</note> of <hi>Rome.</hi> Of which, read Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> who <hi>pag.</hi> 412. proves, That Chriſtianity was planted in <hi>England,</hi> in the Apoſtles time. <hi>Oregine</hi> confeſſeth, That Chriſtianity was in <hi>England</hi> in his time, (on <hi>Ezek. Hom.</hi> 4.) And <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> affirms here it before his time. Some gather ſom ground from 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10. where <hi>Creſcens</hi> is ſent to <hi>Galatia,</hi> concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be <hi>France,</hi> from whence the Goſpel came to us. Mr. <hi>Cambden</hi> tells us from antient Authors, that <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mathea</hi> planted it here: but enough to prove, that our Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal was not from <hi>Rome,</hi> though in after-time the Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Rome</hi> crept in amongſt us, which we have now for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken, and are ordained according to the Goſpel-Rules. Who deſires more ſatisfaction about Miniſters Ordination, let him read the learned Treatiſe of Mr. <hi>John Collins,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Vindiciae Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterii Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelici.</note> proving, That gifted-men ſhould take the Seal of the Church by Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, as <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> did, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. where the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, and not People, ſet them apart; as Chriſt did his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.41. And the Greek word, when applyed to Eccleſiaſtical buſineſs, requires not the peoples conſent: Read Mr. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ines</hi> on 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 20 proving,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ordain Elders without the peoples conſenting, or gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in Suffrages, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.23. Read <hi>Leigh</hi> on the Word: Yet I am not againſt peoples choice alſo, where to be had conveniently. Read the <hi>Diatribé,</hi> printed 1647. proving, that many of our godly Reformers had onely inward Call, and Peoples Suffrages: now as Election makes a King more then his Coronation; ſo peoples Conſent, more then Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination. But I forbear, knowing that the approbation of the Miniſtry (by reaſon of their abilities) is far beyond that of the people. Well! we have Miniſters both ways ſet apart, yet the Baptizers own them not. But ſo much in general about Miniſters, which your Characters cauſed me to ſay: yet you find fault rather with the perſonall faults of the Miniſtry, than with their Office: The Office is good, though a <hi>Cataphas,</hi> or a <hi>Judas</hi> miſcarry in it: He, amongſt you that's without fault, let him throw the firſt ſtone.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:63260:19"/>
               <head>The manner of <hi>Sions</hi> Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption diſcovered.</head>
               <p>NOw I come to examine your <hi>Sion's Redemption;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">How <hi>Sion</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed.</note> in which you plead for the Jews return to their own Countrey. <hi>Brightman</hi> was of that Opinion, and that <hi>Euphrates</hi> therefore is to be miraculouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dryed up, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.<note place="margin">In Rev. 16.</note> that the Jews beyond <hi>Euphrates</hi> may not be hindred in their return: This Opinion <hi>Paraeus</hi> calls godly and probable, but not ſolid. Read my Expoſition of that Chapter, how <hi>Euphrates</hi> ſhall be dryed up: The Jews promiſe themſelves an happy enjoyment of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.<note place="margin">Rab. Men. Ben. Spes Iſrael</note> The learned <hi>Rabbi,</hi> in his <hi>Book</hi> dedicated to our long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liv'd-Parliament, tells us,<note place="margin">The Rabbi is his book, cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led, <hi>Iſraelis.</hi>
                  </note> that the Ten Tribes live together beyond the <hi>Cordiller</hi> Hills, and the River <hi>Maragnon,</hi> differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Religion from the <hi>Indians,</hi> in whoſe Countrey they are. <hi>Sed parvas ſpes habet, Troja, ſi tales habet.</hi> For the Readers ſake,<note place="margin">Chap. 9.15, 16, 17.</note> I ſhall enlarge my ſelf a little on this pleaſant ſubject. The ten Tribes are threatned never to be a people more, in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 7.8. Pray, what hope of their return? And <hi>Hoſea</hi> tells us of the Ten Tribes, God will love them no more (as to return them) God will caſt them away, and they ſhall be wanderers amongſt the Nations.<note place="margin">The Jews re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to <hi>Judae</hi> diſproved.</note> Yet I believe there is hope of their Call, becauſe <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. and that paſſage of <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mars</hi> Children prove in <hi>Gen.</hi> 38.28. <hi>Sarah</hi> might repreſent the Jew, with the ſcarlet Thred, or Sacrifices, who firſt made proffer to ſerve God, as firſt-born, but drew back like a ſtiff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necked people; <hi>Pharez,</hi> in the mean time, ſteps forth, Behold the Gentiles call! but <hi>Zarah</hi> was born at laſt:<note place="margin">Zach. 10.10.</note> the Jew then ſhall be a people belonging to God. Nay, I believe the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſing the Ten Tribes will be a means to gain others to God upon their Call. Hence God is ſaid to ſow them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people, (good ſeed ſhall not periſh) and they ſhall remember me in far Countries.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:63260:20"/>
               <p>Now, though their return to <hi>Gilead,</hi> and to <hi>Lebanon</hi> be there, it muſt be ſpiritual: to wit, to the Church, or Spiritual Hieruſalem, and that Spiritual Land of Promiſe. Read <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notat of Aſſembly</hi> on the place.<note place="margin">Book Ch: 35. pag. 5.</note> Hence, Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi> ſayes of <hi>Iſrael converted; Any Mountain ſhall be their Oliver, River their Jordan, Field their Carmel, Foreſt their Lebanus, Fort their Sion, and City their Jeruſalem.</hi> I am the rather induced to believe this, becauſe <hi>Canaan</hi> was their peculier Land, whiles they, Gods peculiar people: now, the partion wall is broken down. And as for <hi>Judahs</hi> return to the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> the Scripture is flat againſt it; as in <hi>Zach.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.6. <hi>I will no more pitty the Inhabitants of the Land, and out of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies hands I will not deliver them.</hi> And <hi>Jeremy</hi> tells us, God wil break this people,<note place="margin">Chap. 19.11.</note> and this City, as a Potters veſſel, which cannot be made whole again. <hi>Ezekiel</hi> is yet plainer, <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.53, 55. <hi>When Sodom and Gomorrha ſhall be reſtored to their former eſtate, and Samaria to hers, then ſhall Judah's Captivity be reſtored.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Roſsaus, <hi>p. 375.</hi>
                  </note> That will never be; <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> ſayes <hi>Hierom, in aternos collapſa eſt Cineres.</hi> Indeed, the Scepter was to depart from <hi>Iudah</hi> when <hi>Shilo</hi> came. Their houſe is left deſolate now, their Fig-tree curſed, and (wonder it was) their Land by the Romans was ſold: Here was <hi>Digitus Dei,</hi> who ſold no other Land but that, ſayes <hi>Mede.</hi> But it may well be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, That God promiſed them a return out of Captivity, (all his people, to wit) that he would have compaſſion on them, and remember them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.3. <hi>Lev.</hi> 26.44. Anſw. Out of ſeveral calamities he did, and out of the Babyloniſh Captivity: But hithetto they had onely ſtoned the Prophets, and abuſed his ſervants; but when once they had murdered his ſon, his mercies (in returning them) were at an end for evermore. Hence forward any Text (good Reader) that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes the Jews a return, either underſtand it, out of the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byloniſh Captivity, or conſtrue it in a Spiritual ſenſe, That the Jews ſhall return to God, or out of darkneſs, to light, and out of the power of Satan to Chriſt, to enjoy the true <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and Celeſtial Land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> And thus, Friend <hi>Hammond,</hi> your Texts are anſwered; except that of <hi>Eſay</hi> 60. which ſpeaks chiefly of the glorious eſtate of the Church under <hi>Meſsias,</hi> deſcribed by the multitude of proſelytes, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:63260:20"/>thoſe of chief note and place that ſhould be joyned to it; ſo that the Heathens ſhould bring in their riches, and joyn in the ſervice of Chriſt. Hence you perceive, that Propheſie muſt not be taken literally, but ſpiritually: thus underſtand,<note place="margin">The lews not to enjoy their Temple.</note> 
                  <hi>her opened gates,</hi> v. 11. to admit proſelytes and members; and by the City Jeruſalem, the Church. Places which ſound li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terally in the Prophets, muſt be ſpiritually expounded, and applied in the Goſpel. Thus the Apoſtle expounds, <hi>Amos</hi> 9.11. in <hi>Act.</hi> 15.17. You proceed to prove, that <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall have their Temple re-built at their return, becauſe <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſaw a Temple, <hi>Chap.</hi> 41. <hi>v.</hi> 1. But <hi>Ezekiels</hi> Propheſie is ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually to be looked on,<note place="margin">Read Mr. <hi>Th. Fuller, l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> as appears by the miraculous Fruit which never fades, <hi>Chap.</hi> 47.12. And the ſtrange waters in the beginning of that Chapter. Now as was the Waters and Fruit, ſo the Temple, Spirituall. The Temple was a Type, which is ended in Chriſt. The Saints are now the Temple, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. and <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> the Church, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>I come to examine how the Jewes ſhall be converted: You ſay, Not by a Goſpel-Miniſtry; but you greatly erre, not knowing the Scriptures. For,</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. confutes you, where the Apoſtle tells us, That the Goſpel is the power of God to Salvation, to the Jew and Gentile.</p>
               <p>Secondly, There is no other Name under Heaven,<note place="margin">The Iews to be converted by the goſpel.</note> by which men muſt be ſaved, then by the name of Jeſus, <hi>Act.</hi> 4. Now die Name of Chriſt is conveyed to men in a Goſpell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the Jews ſhall (through our mercies) obtain mercy, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.31. that is, through Chriſt and his Goſpel, (for thoſe are our infinite mercies) therefore, without doubt, the Jews are to be called by the Goſpel, and not to wait in their Sacrifices, or Temple, for Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Now, ſhould not theſe Jewes be tolerated amongſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians?</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Becauſe elected, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.28. and beloved.</item>
                  <item>2. Becauſe Chriſtians owe all to them, as having both Law and Goſpel by their means, and we grow on their Root, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.18.</item>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:63260:21"/>
                  <item>3. Becauſe Chriſt left his glory (in part) for their ſakes and he and his Diſciples went after them.</item>
                  <item>4. Becauſe they begin to read Chriſtian Authors. (<hi>Rabbi Menaſſeh Ben Iſrael</hi> quotes <hi>Auguſt. de Doct. Chriſtiana, cap.</hi> 28. <hi>quòd omnes ſunt aequé diligendi,</hi> in his Book dedicated to our Lord Protector, <hi>pag.</hi> 23.</item>
                  <item>5. They will not ſacrifice but at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> as the ſame <hi>Rabbi</hi> teſtifies, <hi>p.</hi> 22.)</item>
                  <item>6. And are no great Uſurers of late,<note place="margin">Tolleration <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f Jews.</note> taking but 4 or 5 <hi>per cent.</hi> as he affirms, <hi>p.</hi> 20. But enough! You proceed to tell us, that the Witneſses in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. are to diſſwade the Jewes from believing in Antichriſt; and not ſo much to preach Chriſt to them: But you do but ſay it; they will never take the Pope for their Meſſiah; and the work of the Witneſſes is to draw people from Antichriſtianiſm, which had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run all; but the Jews were not infected with Popery: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore needed not the Witneſſes help to deliver them from him. I have general acquaintance with a dozen and half of Commentaries on <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. And all believe (as I remember) that the Witneſſes work, was to reform the Church (ſignified by the Temple, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.1, 2.) then over-ſpread with Popery: The Rod, like a Reed, is the * Word. So here your ſecond proof for a Jewiſh Temple is void,<note n="†" place="margin">Read my Expoſition of <hi>Rev.</hi> Ch. 11.</note> becauſe the Temple is not literally to be expounded, but ſpiritually. Other matters in your Argument, are anſwered above, where I proved, that by <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> is meant the Church: So, by the Temple, may the Worſhip be underſtood; and by the Courts, the Prieſts who officiated there, (as <hi>Paraeus</hi> on the place affirms) Yet <hi>Piſcator</hi> thinks by the outward Court,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.</note> the ungodly multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude is meant; whoſe time of Reformation was ſcarce come.</item>
               </list>
               <p>An eaſie Trope will give us leave to call the Court, the people, or to underſtand the people by the Court. Thus we ſay the <hi>Court of Chancery,</hi> and <hi>Sutton Church,</hi> though no peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be there; though not the naked benches or ſtones, make Court or Church.</p>
               <p>I come to your third Argument, to prove a Temple, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Antichriſt ſhall ſit in it, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4. But none but the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63260:21"/>ignorant Paſtor (as he calls himſelf) of the Church at <hi>Bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denden,</hi> took that for a Jewiſh Temple: But for the Church over which Antiechriſt raigned as Lord and King, too too long: of which anon. But ſuppoſe this a Jewiſh Temple, how doth the Apoſtle ſet forth Antichriſts tyranny, by lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he ſate or ſet up his throne there: A poor honour! But he as God ſits, <hi>in Templum Del,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> learnedly ſpeaks) for a Temple, or, inſtead of Temple, Qracle, Prieſt and all. But Chriſt has deſtroyed him, partly, by the Word and Spirit, (that breath of his mouth) and ſhall after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found him, by the brightneſs of his coming to judgment: Till when, Antichriſt will, in ſome meaſure, raign, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Saints 1000. years glory.<note place="margin">The Pope is Antichriſt.</note> But you deny the Pope to be Antichriſt: in troth he is beholding to you: but I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him Antichriſt, (and you a limb of him. But what makes you huddle up ſo many texts together, to prove the man of ſins ariſing? <hi>pag.</hi> 101. I perceive you underſtand not, what is meant by Gog or Magog, like enough fore-runners of Antichriſt, as the little horn was a type of him, in <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. meaning that Tyrant <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes,</hi> (that ſagacious or cunning, but blaſphemous wretch). You quote <hi>Eſay</hi> 14. 13. to be underſtood of Antichriſt, which was plainly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> v. 4. And, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. you will have underſtood of Antichriſt, not the Pope: Have you not been tutor'd by a Jeſuit? But let us try your Reaſons, why the Pope no Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe the Pope, or rather Romiſh <hi>Babylon,</hi> is ſer forth by the name of a Woman: as <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. but Antichriſt is called the Man of ſinne, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Antichriſt is ſet forth with a double form, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 4, 11. As Tyrano, and falſe Prophet; yet but one Beaſt, <hi>v.</hi> 18. So Antichriſt, as Woman, or Whoriſh Church ſeducing; but as Man (<hi>viz</hi> the <hi>Series</hi> of Popes) tyrannizing.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the Romiſh <hi>Babylon</hi> confeſſeth God;<note place="margin">Qui ſcribit ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervum ſervo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum provat ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> tyrannum tyrannorum.</note> but Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt ſhall exalo himſelf above all Gods, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> He ſhall confeſs him in words, but deny in deeds: ſo does Romiſh <hi>Babylon,</hi> or rather Pope, exalting himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Augels and Kings, who are called Gods.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:63260:22"/>
               <p n="3">3. You ſay, That <hi>Romiſh Babylon</hi> ſhall be deſtroyed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the appearance of Chriſt, but Antichriſt ſhall not. <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church ſhall be diminiſhed before Chriſts appearance as Judge; but not quite deſtroyed. Partly, ſhe is deſtroyed by the breath of Chriſts mouth (his word and ſpirit) already, and the reſt by the brightneſs of his comming, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. but you may finde that in <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.17. and chap. 18.18. the City of <hi>Rome</hi> is to be deſtroyed by fire; but the Pope ſhall ſurvive, and the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church (though diminiſhed), till laſt day, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20. plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sancta Maria Regena cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalva nos.</note> I could ſhew you many Arguments to prove the Pope Antichriſt, as 1. Who is againſt the honour, Church, and truth of Chriſt, is Antichriſt; ſuch is the Pope, praying to Saints (which derogates from Chriſt) counting himſelf as head of the Church, remitting ſins, bidding the Virgin Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand her Son, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Who exalts himſelf above all that is called God,<note place="margin">Though he 0204 0725 V call himſelf <hi>Servus ſerve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Dei.</hi>
                  </note> is Antichriſt; but ſo doth the Pope, as above Emperours, Kings, nay Angels, who are called Gods. The <hi>Lateran</hi> Councel applauded the Pope, ſaying, Thou art all things, and above all things. And again, the ſame Councel ſaid to him, thou art another God on earth. Read <hi>Jewels</hi> Apology, page 447. or <hi>Aug. Civit. Dei. l.</hi> 20. <hi>c.</hi> 19. expounding <hi>in Templum;</hi> or, <hi>Annot.</hi> of <hi>Aſſemb.</hi> on 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4.</p>
               <p>But 3 dly. Who ſits in the Seat of Antichriſt, is Antichriſt; but ſo doth the Pope on ſeven hills of <hi>Rome, Rev.</hi> 17.9. where were ſeven Governments, and the Pope the eighth, trading for ſouls of men, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. And in <hi>Johns</hi> time ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling over Nations, (<hi>Rome</hi> to wit, was the now feat, of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,) what need further proof?—From your page 112. to 128. you almoſt trifle away Pen, Ink, and Paper: for my part I ſhall not fight with your ſhadow. Yet a word to what you ſay. You would prove, that upon the laſt return of the Jews to their Country, Antichriſt, which you call <hi>Gog,</hi> out of <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38. ſhall deſtroy or ſpoil <hi>Iſrael,</hi> till Chriſt ſuccour them. But.
<list>
                     <item>1. The Jews finall return to their Country, is diſproved already.</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Gog</hi> is not litterally Antichriſt (though
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:63260:22"/>an enemy to Chriſts Church.)</item>
                  </list>
By <hi>Gog,</hi> underſtand the people of <hi>Aſia,</hi> ſo called from <hi>Giges</hi> the King; by <hi>Magog,</hi> the <hi>Scythians;</hi> and by both underſtand the <hi>Turk</hi> who came of them, and raigns over them. Nov,<note place="margin">Who <hi>Gay</hi> and <hi>Magog.</hi>
                  </note> though the <hi>Gogims</hi> did much ſpoyl <hi>Iſrael</hi> under <hi>Antiochus,</hi> and were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown by the <hi>Macchabees</hi> (God wonderfully aſſiſting) upon the Mountains of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the latter dayes (not the laſt) <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38.16.21: Yet we expect a further deſtruction of the enemies of Gods Church, comprehended under <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog, Turk,</hi> &amp;c. (Read <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.) which will hardly come to paſſe, till Chriſt come to judgement, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.9. when Chriſt ſhall come with flames of fire to deſtroy his enemies. But <hi>Gog</hi> cannot be Antichriſt, becauſe of Unbelieving; for Antichriſt muſt ſit in the Temple, as owning <hi>God,</hi> &amp;c. Now you would prove, that this <hi>Gog</hi> Antichriſt, ſhall be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Chriſt, before the end; and quote <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11.<note place="margin">No wart with Gog on <hi>Iſraels</hi> Mount.</note> to prove it; but that Text is meant of Chriſts comming to judgement, as appears by verſ. 15. the ſword comming out of Chriſts mouth, being his ſentence to the wicked at the laſt day, when he ſhall ſlay them with, <hi>Go ye curſed, &amp;c.</hi> Thus all warres (in the letter) on the Mountains of <hi>Iſrael</hi> are ended.<note place="margin">P. 128.</note> And I come to examine Chriſts perſonall raign in earth 1000. years, when <hi>Gog</hi> and all enemies ſhall be ſubdued to him, where a thouſand to one, but I ſhall finde you tardy. Your grand proof is, becauſe Chriſt was to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the Throne of <hi>David, Luke</hi> 1. which was not ſpirituall but temporall. But conſider, Chriſt tells <hi>Pilate,</hi> that his Kingdom was not of the world, <hi>John</hi> 18.36.<note place="margin">Chriſts perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Raign diſproved as in Earth.</note> in the ſence that <hi>Caeſars</hi> was: ſo Chriſt muſt ſucceed <hi>David</hi> ſpiritually, becauſe alſo, Of his Kingdom there muſt be no end, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.33. Now by <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> there, the Saints are meant, the true <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God: thus he is called King of Saints, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15,—And to this purpoſe, other Texts of Scripture muſt be underſtood, where Chriſt, is called a King: that learned Sermon of Dr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> on <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. (we ſhall raign on earth) ſpeaks louder, and more to purpoſe then all other Books on that ſubject: yet becauſe Chriſts Kingdom was ſpiritual before his aſcenſion, I believe it will be ſo ſtill,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63260:23"/>becauſe the Angels told the Diſciples ſo, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.11. This ſame Jeſus ſhall ſo come in like manner, as you have ſeen him go into Heaven. So that <hi>Paraeus</hi> expounds the Saints raiguing in earth ſpiritually, as they ſhall be Kings and Prieſts, to wit, ſacrifycing ſin, raigning over wicked, by the ſpirit in them; for the head Chriſt raigning, the members raign; but the Weapons of our warfare are not carnall. The Saints raign in earth may be theſe wayes, firſt by their prayers,<note place="margin">Saints Raign ſpirituall.</note> prevailing with God to bring judgements or bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings upon the earth: thus read <hi>Iſay</hi> 45.11. Concerning the works of my hands, command ye me: how did <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> even govern the world by their prayers? to ſay nothing of the witneſſes. (<hi>Rev.</hi> 11-2.) By being admitted into high priviledges in Heaven, of which 2 <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. <hi>Dun.</hi> 4.17. holy ones with Chriſt, carrying on the Government of the world. What think you of <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.10. How long O Lord? But you'l ſay, Saints know not what's done below: (there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can't govern, or raign on earth, whiles in Heaven;) for <hi>Iſay</hi> 63.16. ſayes, <hi>Jacob</hi> knowes us not, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Of themſelves, Saints above cannot tell whats don below,<note place="margin">Saints know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of things below by Angles.</note> becauſe of their remoteneſs, and becauſe without bodies;—but they have acquaintance of the affairs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, by means of Angels, who partly govern this world (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God) <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. Now Angels and Saints can make mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters known to one another, r. <hi>Luke</hi> 15. of joy in Heaven over one penitent ſinner: therefore Heaven (or Saints there) muſt know it. And in <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.20. upon <hi>Babylons</hi> overthrow, Heaven, Prophets, and Apoſtles rejoyce, therefore knew of its overthrow; but enough. The grand objection againſt the ſpirituall raign of Chriſt onely, lies in <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.27. a Kingdom under the whole Heavens ſhall be given to Saints, and v. 18. and v. 14. and this after the Beaſts body is given to be burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ven. 11. But all this may be taken ſpiritually of Chriſts Kingdom upon earth, ruling and raigning in his Church; and thus the Saints building and planting (of Churches, to wit) and eating (<hi>i. e.</hi> feeding in Ordinances) may be ſpirituall: in <hi>Iſay</hi> 65.22. without wreſting the Text; but let us brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly examine <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. The foure Beaſts are the foure King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:63260:23"/>The fourth, ſome take to be, not the <hi>Roman,</hi> but the <hi>Selucidan</hi> Kingdom of <hi>Syria,</hi> called a fourth,<note place="margin">The ſame for ſubſtance with <hi>Alexander,</hi> but differing in ten horns, read <hi>Annor.</hi>
                  </note> becauſe not abſolutely Monarchicall at preſent (for <hi>Macedonia, Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> were Kingdoms alſo in the hands of <hi>Alexanders</hi> ſucceſtors) as the former were, and more terrible to the Land of <hi>Judea</hi> and Saints, which the Beaſt even conſumed, verſe 23. The ten Horns were ten Kings in that Kingdom,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Read</hi> Junius, Eng. Annot. Diodati <hi>on</hi> Dan. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> from <hi>Seleucus</hi> to <hi>Antiochus</hi> (the little Horn) who was the tenth (as <hi>Junius</hi> proves) and laſt, that raigned over <hi>Judaea,</hi> till Chriſts time. Well, in ſumm this Beaſt was ſlain by the <hi>Parthians,</hi> and King <hi>Tygranes</hi> of <hi>Armenia;</hi> and <hi>Syria</hi> made a <hi>Roman</hi> Province by <hi>Pompey:</hi> here is his ruine; meant by his bodies burning by conſuming Warr, verſ. 11, then the Saints time came according to promiſe, v. 18.14.27. quickly was Chriſt born the ſpirituall King; but where's the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Kingdom? Or ſuppoſe, by four Beaſts, the <hi>Roman</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch were meant, and by ten Horns, the ten Kings (or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) in <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.12. (which aroſe out of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monatch) and ſuppoſe the Pope the little horn, typed by that in <hi>Dan</hi> 7. Well, the Beaſt (be it the remainder of the <hi>Roman</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch in <hi>Turke,</hi> Pope,<note place="margin">Read my Expoſition Chap. 19. <hi>Revel.</hi>
                  </note> &amp;c.) and Kings of the earth (who adhered to him) are taken a live (as at laſt day) <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.19, 20. and caſt into Hell fire (I believe): now after this, ſure no Kingdom for Saints, but that above in glory. For though in <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. the apparition of Gods judgement might not ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the day of judgement; but Gods judgement on his then Churches enemies: yet in <hi>Revel.</hi> 19.19 20. all things being well conſidered, the laſt day is meant (after which no tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Kingdom) for Antichriſt and Beaſt ſhall (in ſome ſort) continue to the laſt, as 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. prove, and <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 20. Now whiles theſe raign, where's Saints temporall King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom?</p>
               <p>But it may be demanded, Why were the lives of the other Beaſts prolonged, after their dominion was taken away, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.12. if not, becauſe Chriſt and Saints were temporally to raign over them? as <hi>ver.</hi> 13, 14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 'Tis already plain, that Chriſt took not on him a temporal Kingdom.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:63260:24"/>
               <p n="2">2. The next Monarch prolonged the lives of the peoples (who once belonged to theſe beaſts) to raign over them. Every Empire or Enemy, in their time, periſhed; but the people thereof continued in ſome low form or ſtate, till brought under by the Romans. But Chriſt is not to tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally raign in earth: read <hi>John</hi> 14.2. <hi>I go to prepare a place for ye, (in heaven) that where I am, ye may be (not in earth).</hi> And 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.16. <hi>We ſhall be caught up to Chriſt in the Air (when he comes to raiſe the Dead in Chriſt, who ſhall riſe before the neſt) and to we ſhall be ever with the Lord;</hi> to wit <hi>raigning in the heaven, not on earth.</hi> And <hi>Act.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Whom the heavens ſhall contain, till the time of the reſtitution of all things.</hi> Now, Heaven and Earth is to be reſtored (of which a word anon) but that will not be, till after Wickeds Reſurrection, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12, 13. and Chap. 21.1, 2. compared. For if the Earth be reſtored before wicked's reſurrection, ſhall it be digged up again, or he faced, to raiſe up wicked's bodies? Or muſt not their bodies be part of the glorified Earth? <hi>redime te cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So Chriſt ſhall not come from heaven to raign before wickeds reſurrection, which is againſt your tenet: but 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. makes it plain, <hi>ver.</hi> 23, 24. That Chriſt comes to judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at the end of all, then comes the end: therefore, no time of temporal raigning for Saints after his coming: onely this Caveat I'le add, If Chriſt judge as man, then the day of the Lord may be as a 1000 years; all which time, the Saints ſhall judge the world with Chriſt: But what is this to a temporal raign? Beſides, why ſhould earth be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore heaven to raign in? And if thoſe alive muſt eat and drink (as ſome exound, <hi>Eſay</hi> 65. literally,) is not here E pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curiſm? Sure the Kingdome of God conſiſts not in theſe things, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17. You may oppoſe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. where Saints are ſaid to raign a 1000. years: And 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13. we expect new Heavens, and new Earth, wherein dwells righteouſneſs. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Paraeus in ev. 20. Read y Expoſition, ev. 20.</note> Here is nothing will prove your deſign, * <hi>Paraeus</hi> has anſwered every Objection, and cleared any difficulty about the thouſand years, and firſt reſurrection: briefly, Satan was bound up a thouſand years, as not to hinder the propagation
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:63260:24"/>of the Goſpel (though he raiſed perſecution againſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors thereof). The thouſand years of Satans binding, in probability, began about the ruine of the Jewiſh Temple, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 73. (for while that Temple ſtood, the Jews much withſtood the preaching of thee Goſpl; in which thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years, multitudes of people believed, but were perſetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to death:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> theſe <hi>John</hi> ſees living and raigning with Chriſt (in glory) thoſe thouſand years in which Satan was bound up; their converſion is called the firſt reſurrection, being to grace (many being bodily raiſed in Old and New Teſtamen before) anſwerable to Fall of Soul firſt into ſinne. Now this was the firſt reſurrection or converſion of ſoules to grace in the thouſand years. Remember, <hi>John</hi> ſaw (viſionally) the ſouls (not bodies) in heaven with Chriſt, (not in earth) raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning after Death: Read my Expoſition of that Chapter at large. To that of <hi>Peter</hi> I anſwer; the words may be read thus: <hi>We, in whom dwels righteouſneſs expect a new heaven, and a new earth.</hi> But a word of the renovation of the world; and of this new heaven, &amp;c. and concerning the new Jeruſalem: Of which, <hi>George Hammond</hi> pag. 151. ſpeaks ſtrangely: For he would have it to be a material City; but not made by man but God. I cannot believe it for what City in the Letter can have twelve Foundations, as this has? <hi>v.</hi> 14. Or Angels Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to a material City? as <hi>v.</hi> 12.<note place="margin">Of the new Jeruſalem.</note> How can gates be made of pearl; or how one pearl big enough to make a whole gate? and ſuch like improbabilities. Neither do I think this new Jeruſalem to be that once poſſeſſed by the Jews, and now newly re-edified. Againſt which <hi>George Hammond</hi> uſes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Arguments. But as Mr. <hi>Roberts,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Forbes</hi> agree,<note place="margin">On Rev. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> it may be ſpiritually taken for the ſtate of the Church after the Jews converſion, and after the whore and beaſt, with falſe Prophet, and other enemies, are deſtroyed temporally, not damned. 1. Becauſe the moſt precious things in Nature are too abject (rather then too high) to expreſs the diſpenſation of grace (now at the higheſt.) 2. God is ſaid to have his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle with men <hi>ch.</hi> 21.3. (not men with God) and Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem is ſaid to come down out of heaven, intimating it here below. 3. That here is nothing here ſo magnifiquely ſpoken,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:63260:25"/>which the Prophets have not almoſt in the ſame terms utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the eſtate of the Church here in grace. Of which, read the Authors themſelves on that place. Indeed, I believe a choice time, when the Jews ſhall be converted, called (<hi>Rom.</hi> 11) Life from the Dead: yet ſince the day of judgment ſeems paſt before this City be ſeen;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> as <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.12. and 21.2. and Whore and Antichriſt damned, <hi>Ch.</hi> 19. who were to laſt till Chriſts coming,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8.1 may believe with <hi>Paraeus,</hi> That this City repreſents the ſtate of the Church in glory, becauſe actualled adorned, and ſitted for Chriſt the husband, too high for a ſtare of grace: eſpecially conſidering all tears (and therefore enemies, nay and ſin the cauſe of tears) ſhall be wiped away: yet when the Son of man comes, ſhall he find faith in earth?<note place="margin">Adorned for Husband, and not for Spouſe.</note> 
                  <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in the Viſion, might ſeem to <hi>John</hi> to come down, not locally, but in reſpect of her Originall, which is from heaven. But enough: If we take <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſpiritually, as in earth, then by new Heaven, and new Earth, a new face of the Univerſe may be meant; (for Scripture, by new Heaven, and new Earth, is wont, ſayes Mr. <hi>Roberts,</hi> to expreſs great changes in the world.<note place="margin">Eſay 65.17.66, 22.</note>) Now when Whore, falſe Prophet, and Dragon are deſtroyed, here is a new world or new dweling, for the new Church. The bringing in the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Kingdoms to the Faith, and deſtruction of all enemies of the <hi>Church,</hi> may <hi>wel</hi> be called, <hi>A new Heaven, &amp; new Earth.</hi> But,<note place="margin">Read <hi>Engl. Annot. Diodat.</hi> Key of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, on <hi>Rev.</hi> 21</note> if by <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> we underſtand the ſtate of glory; then by <hi>New Heaven</hi> &amp;c. we underſtand Heaven and Earth, literally by fire to be renewed, according to <hi>Peter,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.21, 22. (the hardeſt text in <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles ſays D. <hi>Hackwel</hi> in <hi>Ap.</hi>) the whole Creature groans; &amp;c. not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. I expect Sun and Moons reſtoring to more light, <hi>Eſay</hi> 30.26. for reward of their unwearied labor, (though you will have Earth dark hereafter, <hi>page</hi> 22.) And I believe Sea may be reſtored, (though not with raging waves, &amp;c.) to ſtand as a Monument of Gods wiſdome, mercy, and power: And I believe the Sons of God, in glory, may viſit theſe. But to expect reſtoring of each Tree, Leaf and Graſſe; nay, or beaſts (in what ſence you pleaſe) for which you ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue <hi>p.</hi> 154. is too carnal and beaſtly, if well examined; they
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:63260:25"/>are not capable of glory: but, in their time, ſhall be freed from bondage; the Heaven and Earth, Sun and Moon, ſhall have that glory they are capable of; but I muſt be brief. Read my Expol. of <hi>Rev. Chap.</hi> 21. for further ſatisfaction. Thus I have done, Friend <hi>Hammond,</hi> as to the ſubſtance of your Book: I intended not to anſwer every trivial Objection, or to open each Text, impertinently quoted by whole Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turies; nay, forced together like <hi>Sampſons</hi> Foxes: I have civilly given them quarter (being violently forced to take up arms againſt the Truth) to return to their proper place in the book of God, to aſſert that cauſe God at firſt command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them. I will not inſtance in any, to ſhew your ignorance, or diſcredit your knowledge; onely that laſt text of <hi>Eſay</hi> 11. <hi>The Lyon ſhall eat with the Oxe,</hi> you produce unadviſedly to prove, the reſtoration of Beaſts (if I underſtand you) which is underſtood of the moſt peaceable government of the Lord Jeſus, in changing our ſavage natures, and making us ſubmit freely to his yoak.<note place="margin">Several paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in ſeverall pages of <hi>Geo: Hammond's</hi> Book; briefly, anſwered.</note> To all the reſt of your <hi>Book</hi> I ſhall ſpeak but in few words: And firſt, to that place in <hi>p.</hi> 149. That as <hi>Adam</hi> had his Earthly Paradiſe; ſo ſhall Chriſt have his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly upon Earth, which is the new Jeruſalem: To which I ſhall agree, if you underſtand the (even) glorious condition of the Church here below upon the Call of the Jews, by the new Jeruſalem: or that glorified condition of the Church above, (for <hi>Adams</hi> Paradiſe was to repreſent the Celeſtiall, in which the Apoſtle was, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4.) but a temporal Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe I deny, as well as Chriſts temporal raign. And when, <hi>p.</hi> 154. you talk of the whole Creations re-enjoying the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that it was in once in <hi>Adams</hi> Innocency, you ſpeak without book; for, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.21, 22. cannot hold it. I ask you, ſhall every Beaſt be ſo reſtored? The world is not able to contain them, no more then the Trees can hold every branch or leafe, or the fields every former graſs. But ſhall onely thoſe Beaſts have this priviledge, who are alive at the laſt day? Pray, why ſhould theſe have ſuch a priviledge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove their fellow-Creatures and Partners in bondage? The World (Heaven and Earth) ſhall be reſtored to their primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:63260:26"/>glory, and better: But doth God take care of Oxen? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.9. but in page 159. you affirm, that Man and Beaſt muſt have a more quiet and peaceable time: for this is a time of perſecution.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Man ſhall hereafter; hardly, here below: For Chriſt, <hi>Mark</hi> 10.30. tells us, Saints have all here (or Grace Faith &amp;c.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> which is, † <hi>inſtar omnium</hi>) with Perſecution but hereafter Eternal Life, here's little peace; though to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the end, the Sea, figuratively, ſhall be no more; that is, troubles, as formerly, according to them, who (by <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lems</hi> coming down from Heaven) hold the Ghurches even glorious and peaceable condition, after her enemies deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p>To what you ſay in page 141. about the Saints poſſeſſing the riches of their Enemies (as true heirs to the riches of the world) I ſay this is a pleaſant,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> but falſe doctrine.</p>
               <p>For though Chriſt reſtored onely the Elect to Celeſtiall priviledges, yet he reſtored all to Temporal. Hence he gave Mount <hi>Seir</hi> to <hi>Eſau,</hi> as really as <hi>Canaan</hi> to <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And <hi>Luk:</hi> 16.25. the Glutton is ſaid to receive his good things. And indeed why ſhould they be barred from Temporals, who have no ſhare in Eternals? p. 168. You ſay that Nationall Congregations are not called the Church of Chriſt; nor her Miniſters, Chriſts Miniſters; and therefore you expect ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kind of Preaching, to convert the Nations towards the end of the world.</p>
               <p>National Miniſters, are called the Angels of the waters, as thoſe waters are expounded,<note place="margin">Read my Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ. of Rev. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.5. and and 17.15. O pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Doctor!</p>
               <p>But did not Chriſt bid his Diſciples,<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>5.</hi> &amp; <hi>17.15.</hi> about Angels of waters.</note> diſcipulize all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>Matth,</hi> laſt. May there then not be a National Church, and National Miniſters in a good ſenſe? Pray, how came ſo many Nations converted, and by whom, if not by Nationall
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:63260:26"/>Miniſters; Such Teachers as you, were not then in being; and 'tis well, if ye are not now born too ſoon. And thus, Friend <hi>Hammond,</hi> I take my leave of you, and your Book; which, like the Apples neer the <hi>Aſphaltite-Lake,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Solnius ca. <hi>48.</hi>
                  </note> ſeem choice and pleaſant: but being handled, moulder to duſt, or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Febr.</hi> 6.1655.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
